<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Programming | Jeremy's Hacker Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jeremymorgan.github.com//"/>
  <updated>2012-11-25T16:53:32-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jeremymorgan.github.com//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremy Morgan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New SEO Tools Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/free-seo-tools/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-14T16:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/new-seo-tools-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you may or may not know I'm an SEO and often write about SEO and Marketing on my website. I decided to start working on a set of tools to put on my site, and I've open sourced them so others can use them and hopefully fork or improve upon.</p>

<p>The repo <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/seotools">is located here</a> and I have a rough start going so far, you can also access the live demo <a href="http://seotools.ironfoundry.me"> on IronFoundry</a>. I hope to add some more cool stuff to this project in the future.</p>

<p>This is a collection of SEO tools for use on an ASP.Net website running at least the 3.0 .Net framework. I only have two tools for now, but plan to add more.</p>

<p>We currently have</p>

<pre><code>Blog Pinger - Pings multiple blog update sites when you've updated your blog
Server Header Checker - Check your server headers for diagnostic purposes
</code></pre>

<p>Future plans:</p>

<pre><code>Code to text ratio tool
html compressor
image optimizer
keyword analyzer
backlink checker
</code></pre>

<p>This project is open to any suggestions or contributions. If you want to change or add anything send a pull request! I hope to be adding more stuff soon</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress Header Adder]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/octopress-header-adder/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-27T16:09:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/octopress-header-adder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just created the <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/Octopress-Header-Adder">Octopress Header Adder</a> today.</p>

<p>This is just a simple ruby script that adds some generic headers for Octopress. Let's say you have a bunch of files from Wordpress or another blog that you created from markup, you can use this utility to add header information to generate Octopress pages.</p>

<p>It's intended for those who convert all their html files to markup, it's a convienent way to drop some headers into it.</p>

<p>To run it, simply type</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">ruby</span> <span class="n">headeradd</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">rb</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>In the folder with your markdown files. It will add a generic header to the beginning of all of them.</p>

<p>I wrote this for someone who had emailed the Octopress mailing list about it, and figured I would share it here, if one person benefits from it then it's worth the 10 minutes I put into it.</p>

<p>Feel free to branch or shoot me ideas for improving it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Ajax Dropdown Demo]]></title>
    <link href="http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/php-ajax-dropdown-list/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-22T13:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jeremymorgan.github.com//blog/programming-projects/php-ajax-dropdown-demo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently created a tutorial on my site for building a <a href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-create-an-ajax-drop-down-menu-with-php-and-mysql/">PHP Ajax dropdown list</a> and detailed some of the steps required so people could get a good understanding of how AJAX works. Naturally these days most people would simply use jQuery or one of the tons of other quality frameworks for something so simple, but the purpose of this was to teach the basics and show you how AJAX works.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="https://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/jeremymorgan/hosted/php-mysql-ajax-tutorial.jpg" title="Custom PHP Ajax Drop Down List" ></p>

<p>You can <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/JM-AjaxDropDownDemo">get the source here</a> and if you fork it or make a more detailed tutorial let me know! I'd love to see what you've done. Please don't use this on a production webserver as it is for demonstration and education only, it's highly insecure and very basic.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
