<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Jeremy's Programming Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-11T20:00:59-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremy Morgan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[C# .Net Tutorials - How to Learn C# Part 7: Classes and Objects]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/c-sharp/how-to-learn-c-sharp-7-classes-objects/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T13:46:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/c-sharp/c-number-net-tutorials-how-to-learn-c-number-part-7-classes-and-objects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this part of my learning C# tutorial series, I&#8217;m going to talk about classes and objects. These are crucial building blocks of applications and knowledge you will need to have as a C# developer.</p>

<h3>Classes and Objects - What&#8217;s the difference?</h3>

<p>A class is a template that creates state and behavior for your types. An object is an instance of that class. The best analogy I&#8217;ve heard is the cookie cutter analogy: a class is the cookie cutter itself. It defines the shape of the cookie, and the cookies you produce are objects. For instance you may have a star shaped cookie cutter, rectangular or round. Each of those could be classes, and the object (the cookie) is an instance of those classes.</p>

<p>You can create multiple instances of a class (objects) and each one holds a different state, but has the same behaviors as the class as defined. Classes define types, and objects are an instance of that type.</p>

<h3>What is a class?</h3>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hazardous Attitudes in Software Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/hazardous-attitudes-in-software-development/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-07T16:20:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/hazardous-attitudes-in-software-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With software projects it&#8217;s rare that a failure can be pointed a single cause, or a certain person. Usually it&#8217;s a culmination of many smaller mistakes. With technology and formal project management, best practices are usually well documented and available, but one thing that isn&#8217;t talked about as much is attitude. The attitude of persons in your group or your group as a whole is one of the biggest factors of your success.</p>

<p>As a volunteer firefighter my training often intersects with my career in development. It happens more than you might think, and today while taking a class (L-180 Wildland Fire Leadership Development) I learned about a set of &#8220;hazardous attitudes&#8221; that can often get teams in trouble. Reading through it I could see the parallel with software development very clearly. These attitudes on the fireground can get yourself or others killed, so they&#8217;re especially important for everyone to keep in mind, but why not apply them seriously to software development?</p>

<h3>Hazardous Attitudes</h3>

<p>Here is the list of some hazardous attitudes from the class, and this is what we&#8217;ll be applying to software projects.</p>

<ul>
<li>Invulnerability</li>
<li>Anti-Authority</li>
<li>Impulsiveness</li>
<li>Macho (competitive)</li>
<li>Resignation</li>
<li>Complacency (casualness)</li>
<li>Escalation of commitment (target, fixation, mission-itis)</li>
<li>Other ( sexist, racist, agency bias )</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&#8217;ve ever worked on a group project of any type, you&#8217;ve seen these. These types of attitudes also tank software projects just as bad.</p>

<br />


<h4>Invulnerability</h4>

<p>&#8220;This would never happen to us&#8221;. Very common especially with teams who have had some level of previous success. They know of the pitfalls, know the risks and still take chances thinking the worst won&#8217;t happen to them. While this might work for a while or even a long time, the backfire can be devastating. Because you took a risk you know you shouldn&#8217;t have it looks very bad when it fails. You are guaranteed to hear the phrase &#8220;You should have known better&#8221;.</p>

<br />


<h4>Anti-Authority</h4>

<p>&#8220;Those guys are a bunch of idiots!&#8221; These words are often uttered about executives, directors, VPs and other forms of upper management. While it may be true that you know more details about your job, there&#8217;s a really good chance you don&#8217;t know what they know about the business, and the reasons behind their leadership decisions. While it&#8217;s healthy to question policy and ask questions of your leadership, willful denial of their rules or requests can be detrimental to your project, and your employment status. When this attitude gets carried away bad things tend to happen.</p>

<br />


<h4>Impulsiveness</h4>

<p>&#8220;Let&#8217;s just do it! Shoot from the hip!&#8221; This attitude is sometimes disguised well as a &#8220;can do&#8221; attitude. Often times impulsive managers and staff are referred to as &#8220;go getters&#8221; who really get work done. While that may often be the case, truly impulsive decisions that aren&#8217;t well thought out lead you down paths that are very difficult to get out of. Remember it&#8217;s not just the immediate decision that can backfire, it&#8217;s often the subsequent actions and decisions that really get you into trouble with this attitude.</p>

<br />


<h4>Macho (Competitive)</h4>

<p>&#8220;We&#8217;ll really show them how it&#8217;s done&#8221;. This attitude gets you in trouble mostly because you are using a bias, and it&#8217;s another dangerous road to go down. You may get overconfident and step on a lot of toes thinking you&#8217;re going to hit a home run, and then everyone will forget earlier transgressions cheer your victory. This rarely happens in practice. What usually happens is you alienate people who could be collaborating with and destroying your reputation when you fail.</p>

<br />


<h4>Resignation</h4>

<p>&#8220;This is never going to work anyway, so why try?&#8221;. While the downsides to this attitude is pretty obvious, what most people don&#8217;t consider is how well this can take hold and spin out of your control. A single team member who possesses this attitude can eventually infect the whole group. If not corrected, this attitude becomes a self fulfilling prophecy very quickly.</p>

<br />


<h4>Complacency</h4>

<p>&#8220;I&#8217;ve done this a million times&#8221;. Many folks possess this attitude after getting good at something. When working at a lumber mill I was told the people who get injured the most are the ones with the most repetitive jobs that they&#8217;ve been doing forever. They simply quit caring and become complacent to the point they aren&#8217;t paying attention to what they&#8217;re doing. In the business world this can lead to serious bugs and security problems being introduced. Complacent team members are among the most well known.</p>

<br />


<h4>Escalation of Commitment</h4>

<p>&#8220;Well, we&#8217;ve come this far so we as well keep going!&#8221;. This attitude may have the best of intentions, but we usually end up in projects that are over budget and way beyond the deadline. Remember Brooks&#8217; law? Adding more programmers to a late project usually makes it later. And usually the action taken with a failing project is to start throwing money, time and programmers at it until it finishes and nobody is happy with the final product.</p>

<p>Sometimes you just have to know when it&#8217;s time to go back to the drawing board.</p>

<br />


<h4>Other (sexist, racist, agency bias)</h4>

<p>Remove &#8220;agency&#8221; and replace it with &#8220;group&#8221; and you have a problem that&#8217;s extremely common in today&#8217;s business environment. &#8220;Those marketing idiots! Those salespeople!&#8221;. This kind of bias doesn&#8217;t help anyone involved. You should be sharing a common goal not fighting against each other.</p>

<p>Racism and sexism? Remember you&#8217;re a professional, and it&#8217;s 2013. These views are antiquated and ignorant. These views towards your coworkers only creates a bias that harms everyone around you, and your decisions should never be based on them. Not only should you not harbor this bias but you should not allow others to do it. There&#8217;s a reason people can be fired immediately for racist or sexist comments, it&#8217;s a poison that destroys groups, companies, and morale. It inflicts personal damage to others. Be better than that.</p>

<br />


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Reading through these hazardous attitudes it&#8217;s very likely you&#8217;ve already seen it in action. If you have any of these attitudes you&#8217;re contributing to the destruction of your project and group. If you see these attitudes in others and take no steps to correct it you&#8217;re also doing harm. Their is no single recipe for guaranteed software project success, but attitude is a key element. If you have the problems, fix them. If you see it, say something. Lead by example and remember success favors the prepared.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Road To Technical Debt is Paved With Good Intentions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/what-is-technical-debt/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T19:40:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/what-is-technical-debt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What is Technical Debt?</h2>

<p>Technical debt is a metaphor for the result of taking shortcuts in your development that you&#8217;ll have to fix later, creating &#8220;debt&#8221; that has to be paid off. In keeping with that metaphor you often have &#8220;interest&#8221; that must be paid on that debt whenever extra time is added to work around the bad implementation in the first place. It usually starts with the phrase &#8220;we&#8217;ll fix that later&#8221; and often goes unresolved.</p>

<p>Technical debt usually takes some time to manifest, but once it does you&#8217;ll find yourself spending an exponentially larger amount of time creating workarounds.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s an example:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/technical-debt-1.jpg" title="Technical Debt" ></p>

<p>In this diagram we can see a couple of applications. As you can see we have a common database class that has abstracted methods to connect to the database. This is good practice, as these functions are often repeated across applications.</p>

<h2>How Technical Debt Happens</h2>

<p>Technical debt is a long and slow process that rarely happens overnight. But a few bad decisions up front can lead to larger problems later.</p>

<h3>The beginnings</h3>

<p>As application 1 is being developed, the programmer takes the wise choice of creating an abstract database connector he or she can reuse later. The class is developed to accept parameters defining each connection. Then the programmer moves on and creates the rest of application 1.</p>

<p>During testing it&#8217;s found that the database returns some strange results under certain circumstances. The programmer evaluates the problem and determines they can do one of two things:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Fix the problem by altering the database schema and reworking the code to properly handle this case. This may take a few days.</p></li>
<li><p>Hack up a quick fix that works around the issue and only takes an hour.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>About this time the project manager says the CEO is waiting for this application and it needs to be finished promptly. The developer remembers that there are still 5 more features that need to be added and the design needs to be finished. &#8220;I&#8217;ll do the workaround then fix it later&#8221;. We&#8217;ve all been there, including me. The programmer has saved 3 days of valuable development time, but the application gets completed and we move on.</p>

<h3>Piling it up</h3>

<p>So now a few months later we start to develop application 2. Remembering we have our database class already completed, we simply extend and develop application 2. We layout a model, and build our framework and start testing our application. Suddenly we notice that there is some strange output again from that same database query method. What should we do?</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Fix the problem by altering two database schemas and reworking the code on both projects to properly handle this case. We must coordinate our change so that there are no unexpected side effects from this refactoring. This may take a week.</p></li>
<li><p>Hack up a quick fix that works around the issue and only takes an hour.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Again the programmer feels the pressure from a looming deadline. We don&#8217;t want to explain to the boss why there is a delay, and that it&#8217;s our fault. So it gets hacked and duct taped again.</p>

<h3>Now we&#8217;re underwater</h3>

<p>A year later, we have 6 applications that are all sharing different abstracted parts of code. We have attempted to refactor the database class a couple times and it ended up breaking parts of the other applications. So we put workarounds on top of our workarounds. We make small changes for one application and the others go down. The CEO sees it and is rightly furious. How can we fix it? Wipe it out and start over?</p>

<p>At this point you&#8217;re looking at weeks or possibly months of work. During this time no new projects will be completed. It&#8217;s dead time that&#8217;s impossible to justify to your management. Yet project number 7 is an application that ostensibly should take 2 weeks, and instead it&#8217;s taken 6. The project manager is furious, the developers are unhappy and the software is a mess. So who is at fault? Everyone involved. Poor planning, unrealistic expectations and shortcuts is what got us to this point.</p>

<h2>So how do we avoid this?</h2>

<p>If you ask ten programmers how to avoid and fix this you&#8217;ll probably get ten different answers. There have been debates for decades about it, but one thing most can agree on is the fact that shortcuts are bad. Here are a few ways to avoid this problem.</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Create a programmer utopia</strong> - All programmers are given as much time as they need to develop perfect code that applies all the best practices and teachings of the last 50 years of academic research on software development. It might take months for a simple CRUD app, but rest assured it will be the most beautiful and perfect CRUD app you&#8217;ve ever laid eyes on.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Silo development for everything</strong> - Create software on an ad-hoc basis and reuse nothing. Abstract nothing, and build every application as a self standing independent application. Each application is developed by a single person for a single purpose. Don&#8217;t ever try to change platforms, databases or languages used and avoid any broad changes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Do it right the first time</strong> - Plan your software as much as you can. Establish requirements and stick to them. Build with future scaling and reuse in mind. Decouple as much as possible, reuse what you can and test accordingly. If you have a problem, refactor and fix it as soon as possible, and don&#8217;t stop working on it until it is right. Test everything and retest it every single time a change is made.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>So which one do you think you should choose? I have over simplified it here for the sake of brevity but these are all good ways to avoid the technical debt sinkhole that so many companies end up in.</p>

<p>Here are some hard fast rules:</p>

<ul>
<li>Establish realistic expectations</li>
<li>Gather requirements and get them in writing.</li>
<li>Set priorities and stick to them.</li>
<li>Plan for the worst, it might happen.</li>
<li>Plan for change, it will happen.</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t rely on workarounds</li>
<li>Test. Use structured, measurable testing techniques</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t wait to refactor</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t patch it to push it out the door</li>
<li>Don&#8217;t overlook fixes because features were added</li>
</ul>


<h3>Who is at fault for technical debt again?</h3>

<p>  Technical debt is usually the fault of nearly everyone involved in a project. It starts with unrealistic expectations from management, increased pressure from project managers, and programmers who are either under the gun, lazy, inexperienced, or some combination of those factors.</p>

<p>  But these things all stem from the good intentions of everyone involved. The CEO wants to ensure the survival and growth of the company. Management wants to make sure goals are met at a reasonable expense for the company. Project managers want to produce lots of work to show management they&#8217;re making it happen. Programmers want to create cool stuff. Everyone wants to produce things (if they don&#8217;t they shouldn&#8217;t be working there) but experience teaches us how to collaborate to make it work.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Technical debt is a killer. It wastes your company resources, angers your boss, confuses your project managers. It causes programmers to become frustrated and lose pride in their work. It causes projects to take longer and longer to develop.</p>

<p>The power is in your hands as a programmer to push back and try to avoid this pitfall. A simple investment of time up front can prevent massive problems later on. If you inherit technical debt (at some point in your career you will) you absolutely need to make the case to freeze development and fix problems, even if it&#8217;s just one small problem at a time. In fact, that may be the only way you&#8217;ll ever get it done. One method at a time.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll expand on this more soon and expand on some of these points. Be sure to subscribe to my feed to get more articles like this.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install Magento on Windows Azure]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/windows-azure/how-to-install-magento-windows-azure/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-19T13:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/windows-azure/how-to-install-magento-on-windows-azure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&#8217;m going to show you how to set up Magento with Ubuntu 13.04 on Windows Azure. Scalability and performance are always a concern with Magento, and one way you can rectify that is to throw some more server power at it. Windows Azure is great for this purpose.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Why Azure?</h3>

<p>While traditionally used for Microsoft Development, Linux Virtual Machines are available on Azure. One of the biggest complaints about Magento is speed and Azure handles it quite nicely. When Magento sites start getting a lot of products and / or traffic they tend to slow, with Azure you can easily scale up and load balance across many machines to solve that problem.</p>

<p>You can also split up application and the database servers and scale more VMs for each until you get the performance you&#8217;re looking for. It&#8217;s always good to have room to grow in an easy and affordable fashion.</p>

<h3>Getting Started</h3>

<p>First, you&#8217;ll need to create a virtual machine on Windows Azure. This is pretty easy.</p>

<p>From the Windows Azure Portal,</p>

<ul>
<li>Select &#8220;Virtual Machines&#8221; from the button on the left hand side.</li>
<li>Click &#8220;Create a virtual Machine&#8221;</li>
<li>Select Compute -> Virtual Machine -> Quick Create</li>
<li>Select &#8220;Ubuntu Server 13.04&#8221;</li>
<li>Create a name for your service, and enter a password</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-1.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>After your machine is created, select the arrow next to the name to access the Quick Start page.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-2.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<ul>
<li>Select &#8220;Endpoints&#8221;</li>
<li>Select &#8220;Add standalone endpoint&#8221;</li>
<li>Select &#8220;Name: http&#8221;</li>
<li>Save changes (check mark)</li>
</ul>


<p>This will create a http endpoint so you can access the web. It should now show the http endpoint in addition to the ssh endpoint, which we&#8217;ll use in a minute.</p>

<h3>Connect to your Virtual Machine</h3>

<p>Now we&#8217;ll want to connect to your virtual machine through ssh. If you&#8217;re using Linux or a Mac, it&#8217;s already installed, if you&#8217;re using Windows I recommend Putty for this purpose.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">ssh azureuser@[ your cloudapp url ]</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Let&#8217;s get started!</p>

<h4>Step 1: Add MariaDB Repositories</h4>

<p>We need to enter a few commands here to add the MariaDB repository. MariaDB is the database we&#8217;re going to use for Magento, it&#8217;s a drop in place swap for MySQL that&#8217;s better and more secure, so that&#8217;s what we&#8217;ll use. Magento will never know the difference.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install software-properties-common</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-key adv --recv-keys --keyserver keyserver.ubuntu.com 0xcbcb082a1bb943db</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo add-apt-repository &#39;deb http://ftp.osuosl.org/pub/mariadb/repo/5.5/ubuntu raring main&#39;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get update</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h4>Step 2: Install the Web Server</h4>

<p>We&#8217;re going to install Apache with PHP 5 to support Magento on this machine, as well as MySQL connectors, and the maria Database server with the following commands:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install apache2</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install php5 libapache2-mod-php5</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install php5-mysql</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install mariadb-server</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo apt-get install php5-mysql php5-curl php5-mcrypt php5-gd php5-common php-apc</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>During the install you will see the following screen asking for a root password.
<img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-3.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>Set this password and keep a note of it, we&#8217;ll be using it very shortly.</p>

<h4>Step 3: Install Magento</h4>

<p>For this you&#8217;ll need to download the Magento tarball here and put it on your server, or you can use the wget command below. I&#8217;m currently hosting the 1.8.0.0 version.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">cd /var/www</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo wget http://www.jeremymorgan.com/hosted/magento-1.8.0.0.tar.gz </span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo tar -zxvf magento-1.8.0.0.tar.gz </span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo mv magento/* magento/.htaccess .</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now we&#8217;ll need to set the permissions so Magento can write the files it needs to:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo chmod -R o+w media var</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo chmod o+w app/etc</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You&#8217;re set! now let&#8217;s create the database.</p>

<h4>Step 4: Create the Database</h4>

<p>Now we want to create a MariaDB database for this. First, since we just installed this database we want to run a quick script that will make it more secure. Run the following script and answer yes to all the questions:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo mysql_secure_installation</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now we need to create our tables and a user for Magento.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">mysql -u root -p</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once logged in, you&#8217;ll want to create the database, and a user:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">CREATE DATABASE magento;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="go">CREATE USER magentouser IDENTIFIED BY &#39;(enter a password here)&#39;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now we want to assign that user to the database and give it the proper permissions:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">GRANT SELECT, INSERT, CREATE, ALTER, UPDATE, DELETE, LOCK TABLES on magento.* to magentouser;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>now type in &#8220;quit&#8221; to exit MariaDb.</p>

<h4>Step 5: Final Server Configuration</h4>

<p>We want to enable search engine friendly URLs in our install, so run the following command to install mod_rewrite for Apache:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo a2enmod rewrite</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now, we need to open up this file to enable it:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo nano /etc/apache2/sites-available/default</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Change &#8220;AllowOverride None&#8221; to &#8220;AllowOverride All&#8221; so it looks like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-4.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>Save the file and quit.</p>

<p>Now restart the server:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='console'><span class='line'><span class="go">sudo service apache2 restart</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Load it up in a web browser and let&#8217;s get this configured!</p>

<h4>Step 6: Set up Magento</h4>

<p>Now we have Magento all set up and ready to go. Load up the url (whatever name you chose) in web browser and start the installation.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-5.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>Click I agree on the first screen, and continue on the next.</p>

<p>On the next screen, enter your database name, user name and user password in the Database Connection box. You created these earlier on the MariaDB setup.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-6.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>in the web access options, make sure &#8220;Use Web Server (Apache) Rewrites&#8221; is checked</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-7.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>Click Continue.</p>

<p>You will now set up your admin information:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/windows-azure-magento-8.jpg" title="Install Windows Azure on Magento" ></p>

<p>Click Continue and you&#8217;re done!</p>

<p>You can now log into to your admin panel (yourname.cloudapp.net/admin) and get started!</p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>I hope this helps to get your Magento site up and running on Windows Azure. With the load balancing and scaling capabilities this could be an awesome solution for your e-commerce site. Traditionally expansion has been tough and expensive for small and medium businesses who run software like this, but Windows Azure and other cloud based solutions are making it easier and cheaper to expand.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re looking for a durable and scalable solution for your e-commerce needs I would recommend trying this approach.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Create a Cloud Service with Windows Azure]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/windows-azure/how-to-create-a-cloud-service-with-azure/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T17:31:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/windows-azure/how-to-create-a-cloud-service-with-azure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&#8217;m going to show you how I created a cloud service with Microsoft Windows Azure. It&#8217;s pretty easy, and the tools are great to work with. I am putting the code up on <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/ipcountrycode">GitHub</a> if you want to extend or experiment with it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<h3>About this tutorial</h3>

<p>For this tutorial we&#8217;ll be building a web service that is an API that returns country codes for a given IP. It takes the IP in string format and returns a JSON object with country codes in it. This can also be run as a regular ASP.Net website as well.</p>

<p>This web service will:</p>

<p>Take an IP address and turn it into an Integer
Search through integer ranges in a database
find the corresponding country code for that range
return the country code and name in JSON format.</p>

<p>This service is meant as an exercise, but could actually be a useful service if you want to tailor your website content to different countries.</p>

<h3>What you&#8217;ll need</h3>

<p>For this tutorial I&#8217;m using Visual Studio 2012 and a Windows Azure account. If you haven&#8217;t already you can sign up for a free trial of Windows Azure, and check out what they have to offer.</p>

<p>For interfacing with Azure, you&#8217;ll need to get the Windows Azure SDK:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/p/?linkid=313927&amp;clcid=0x409">SDK For Visual Studio 2013 Preview / RC</a></li>
<li><a href="http://http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?linkid=254364&amp;clcid=0x409">SDK For Visual Studio 2012</a></li>
<li><a href="http://go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?linkid=254269&amp;clcid=0x409">SDK For Visual Studio 2010</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Remember in order to run the Azure emulator you will need to run Visual Studio in Administrator Mode.</p>

<h3>Get Started - Create your Cloud Service</h3>

<p>Log in to your Windows Azure portal, and there you&#8217;ll see a list of options. Click on the &#8220;Cloud Services Option&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-1.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click &#8220;Create a cloud service&#8221;.</p>

<p>You will see a screen that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-2.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>You can use the quick create, choose your URL and subscription. If you&#8217;re using the free trial it will show up here, select that and click &#8220;create a cloud service&#8221;.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-3.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Now you should see your service listed under whatever you named it. Click the arrow next to the name to see the welcome page for that service.</p>

<h3>Create your Database Back End</h3>

<p>For this project we&#8217;ll need to create a database backend for our IP addresses and how they&#8217;ll relate to country codes. Your project may not even need a database but if you&#8217;d like to build this project you&#8217;ll have to pay special attention to this part as it&#8217;s a little different than a standard MS-SQL database.</p>

<p>on &#8220;SQL Databases&#8221; in the menu on the left hand side.</p>

<p>Click &#8220;Create a SQL Database&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-4.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Here, when you create a new database, you&#8217;ll need to name it. Select &#8220;1GB&#8221; as the database size, you won&#8217;t need much.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-5.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Here is where you&#8217;ll create your database credentials.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-6.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Make sure &#8220;Allow Windows Azure Services to Access the Server&#8221; is checked. Keep a note of your authentication info because you&#8217;ll need it later.</p>

<p>You will now see your SQL Server listed amongst your SQL databases.</p>

<p>You can now connect to this database with <a href="http://http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/data/tools.aspx">Microsoft SQL Server Management Studio</a>.</p>

<h3>Connect to your SQL Server</h3>

<p>In order to connect to your server, you will need to change the firewall rules to allow access. Look for this link:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-7.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Setting up is really easy, it will pop up the following message:</p>

<blockquote><p>The current IP address xx.xxx.xxx.xxx is not included in existing firewall rules. Do you want to update the firewall rules?</p></blockquote>

<p>Select Yes. On the welcome page, you&#8217;ll see some info you&#8217;ll need to connect:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-8.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Copy this information for SQL Server Management Studio, which we&#8217;ll open next.</p>

<h3>Open Microsoft SQL Server Management Studio</h3>

<p>You will now connect to the server you just created, it isn&#8217;t much different from any other SQL server:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-9.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Replace [SERVERNAME] with the name of your database server, and make sure to put username@[SERVERNAME] as your login. Connect to the server.</p>

<p>Now open up a new query window, and copy in the SQL found from <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/ipcountrycode/blob/master/SQL/createdb.sql">this file</a> which will create our database.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-10.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>I won&#8217;t go into a lot of details just yet, but this is what will be required for our iplookup function, as it will turn an IP into an integer and look it up via this table.</p>

<h3>Import data into our table</h3>

<p>Now we need to import the iplookup data into our table. I have created a .CSV for this purpose here.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/ipcountrycode/tree/master/SQL">Download the SQL and CSV for this tutorial here</a>.</p>

<p>Open up the SQL Server Import and Export Wizard ( <a href="http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms140052.aspx">More info here</a> )</p>

<p>For your data source, select &#8220;flat file source&#8221; and browse to the .CSV file you just downloaded.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-11.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Select &#8220;Advanced&#8221;</p>

<p>Make sure the column names match those in the database, and the screen should look like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-12.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>These column names and types are very important, and should be:</p>

<ul>
<li>id numeric</li>
<li>ipStart eight-byte unsigned integer</li>
<li>ipEnd eight-byte unsigned integer</li>
<li>CountryCode String (width 4)</li>
<li>CountryName String (width 50)</li>
</ul>


<p>Take a look at the preview, it should look like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-13.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click Next.</p>

<h4>Select your destination</h4>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-14.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Here is where we put the authentication information for the SQL server, which is the same as you used for SQL Server Management Studio. Click Next.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-15.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>On the next window you&#8217;ll see mappings. Click on the &#8220;Edit Mappings&#8221; Button. Make sure it looks exactly like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-16.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click Next. You may see some warnings, but it&#8217;s ok it will go through. Click &#8220;run now&#8221; and go have an Orange Soda. Depending on your internet connection it could take a while.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-17.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Now you should have a database loaded with our IP decimal ranges to country codes.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-18.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Now, we&#8217;re ready to write a service to interface with it!</p>

<h3>Building the Web Service in Visual Studio 2012</h3>

<p>By now you should have installed the Microsoft Azure SDK for Visual Studio 2012 and restarted it. Open up Visual Studio and create a new project.</p>

<p>Under Templates, we want to select <em>Visual C# -> Cloud -> Windows Azure Cloud Service</em></p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-19.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>In the next screen, select ASP.NET MVC4 Web Role:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-20.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Then select &#8220;Web API&#8221;</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-21.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click &#8220;OK&#8221; to create your new project.</p>

<h4>Change the welcome page</h4>

<p>One of the first things I&#8217;ll do is change the welcome page, so it doesn&#8217;t have that default web API page.</p>

<p>Click to MvcWebRole1 -> Views -> Home</p>

<p>and open Index.cshtml</p>

<p>I just put in the following code, just to keep it simple:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;h1&gt;IP Country Code Lookup&lt;/h1&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Usage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://ipcountrylookup.cloudapp.net/api/ApiCountryCode/?get&amp;ip=[IP ADDRESS]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Save the file.</p>

<h4>Create the Model</h4>

<p>We&#8217;re going to create a model that can access our database.</p>

<p>Right click on the Models folder, and select <em>&#8220;Add&#8221; -> New item</em>.</p>

<p>Select Data -> ADO.NET Entity Data Model</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-22.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve named mine ipcountrylookup.edmx</p>

<p>Now select &#8220;Generate from database&#8221; and click next.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-23.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>From this screen, we will want to set up a new connection to your Azure database. Click &#8220;New Connection&#8221; and enter in your database credentials:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-24.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click ok.</p>

<p>In the next screen, make sure everything looks correct. Also, check the box to save sensitive data in the connection string. Generally for production applications you do not want to do this, but for learning purposes it will speed things up. Save your entity connections in Web.Config as &#8220;ipcountryEntities&#8221;. Click next.</p>

<p>In the next screen, you&#8217;ll want to select your table &#8220;iptocountry&#8221; and click next. You&#8217;ll see a data model that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-25.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Make sure and build your project after this, so the model shows up in the next dialog boxes.</p>

<h3>Add your controller</h3>

<p>The controller is where it will all come together.</p>

<p>Right click on the controllers folder, and select Add -> Controller</p>

<p>Make sure the following options are selected:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-28.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click add.</p>

<p>Now open up ApiCountryCodeController.cs in the Controllers folder.</p>

<p>We can delete the other methods here, as this is not going to be a fully RESTful api. Remove the PUT, POST and DELETE methods:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-29.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>You can also delete this method, as it will just return a huge array of all the rows:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-30.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Now you should be left to the single getiptocountry method. Let&#8217;s work on that.</p>

<h3>Getiptocountry method</h3>

<p>The way this works now, won&#8217;t really work for what we need. We need a method that will:</p>

<ul>
<li>take an IP address as a parameter</li>
<li>convert that ip address to an integer</li>
<li>do a lookup in the database to find the proper range</li>
<li>find the country code for that range</li>
<li>return the country code</li>
</ul>


<p>It sounds pretty simple, and it is pretty straightforward. But after playing and experimenting with things I made a few mistakes and came up with a pretty clean method of doing it. We&#8217;ll build that method now.</p>

<p>The first thing we need to do is change the input parameter of this function to a string like so:</p>

<pre><code>public iptocountry Getiptocountry(string ip)
</code></pre>

<p>This will make it so we can pass in the IP address as the string. Then, we need to convert that into an integer.</p>

<pre><code>int intAddress = BitConverter.ToInt32(IPAddress.Parse(ip).GetAddressBytes().Reverse().ToArray(), 0);
</code></pre>

<p>Now we&#8217;ll perform our query to get the country code for that IP range by quering our entity:</p>

<pre><code>iptocountry iptocountry = db.iptocountries.Single(i =i.ipStart &lt;= intAddress &amp;&amp; i.ipEnd &gt;= intAddress);
</code></pre>

<p>We can keep the last lines the same. So your full method will look like this:</p>

<pre><code> // GET api/ApiCountryCode/10.0.0.1

public iptocountry Getiptocountry(string ip)
{
int intAddress = BitConverter.ToInt32(IPAddress.Parse(ip).GetAddressBytes().Reverse().ToArray(), 0);

iptocountry iptocountry = db.iptocountries.Single(i =&gt; i.ipStart &lt;= intAddress &amp;&amp; i.ipEnd &gt;= intAddress);

if (iptocountry == null)
{
throw new HttpResponseException(Request.CreateResponse(HttpStatusCode.NotFound));
}

return iptocountry;
}
</code></pre>

<p>Build it, and you&#8217;re almost ready.</p>

<h4>Make it output JSON</h4>

<p>For the next part, we want to make sure our output is in JSON format. To do that, we&#8217;ll need to open up Global.asax in the MvcWebRole root, and add the following line below your Bundleconfig registration:</p>

<pre><code>GlobalConfiguration.Configuration.Formatters.XmlFormatter.SupportedMediaTypes.Clear(); 
</code></pre>

<p>The entire method should now look like this:</p>

<pre><code>protected void Application_Start()
{
    AreaRegistration.RegisterAllAreas();

    WebApiConfig.Register(GlobalConfiguration.Configuration);
    FilterConfig.RegisterGlobalFilters(GlobalFilters.Filters);
    RouteConfig.RegisterRoutes(RouteTable.Routes);
    BundleConfig.RegisterBundles(BundleTable.Bundles);
    GlobalConfiguration.Configuration.Formatters.XmlFormatter.SupportedMediaTypes.Clear(); 
}
</code></pre>

<p>Save the file.</p>

<p>Now, let&#8217;s run our application and try it out. Note that you do have to run Visual Studio 2012 as an Administrator to get the Azure Emulator to work properly.</p>

<p>Now, run the application. Use this for your URL</p>

<pre><code>http://127.0.0.1:81/api/ApiCountryCode/get?ip=10.0.0.1
</code></pre>

<p>You will see output in your browser like this: (Chrome)</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-31.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Note the JSON output, and what you&#8217;re looking for are the countryCode and countryName outputs. These are what we&#8217;ll be looking for when referencing each IP.</p>

<p>Now, lets publish it to Azure.</p>

<h3>Publish the service to Windows Azure</h3>

<p>First, build the solution again, and go to the build menu, and select &#8220;Publish to Windows Azure&#8221;.</p>

<p>You will see a screen that asks for credentials:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-32.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>Click on &#8220;sign in to download credentials&#8221;.</p>

<p>You&#8217;ll then be directed to download a file, that is your &#8220;Publishsettings&#8221; file. Save that in your documents, or somewhere you can find it.</p>

<p>Now, on that same window, import your credentials. Choose your subscription and press next.</p>

<p>If you get a window that says &#8220;Create a storage service&#8221; put in the name of your application and select a location, then press OK.</p>

<p>Here you will get the next configuration screen:
<img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-cloud-azure-33.jpg" alt="How to create a cloud service with Microsoft Azure" /></p>

<p>As you start to develop applications this feature comes in handy. You won&#8217;t always be deploying straight to production, so Visual Studio gives you the option to place the build in different areas. This is pretty nice. For now we&#8217;ll drop it into production.</p>

<p>Click Next, review the options and click &#8220;publish&#8221;.</p>

<p>One of the things you&#8217;ll notice is the first publish takes a long time. That&#8217;s because every file and the entire build is pushed up, future builds won&#8217;t take nearly as long.</p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>I hope this has helped you learn some of the basics of building and deploying a cloud service in Windows Azure. I tried to cover the database creation and data insertion parts, the application creation and deployment. It&#8217;s a front to back look at what it takes to create a cloud service.</p>

<p>Why a cloud service? As I said this application could just as easily be put on an ASP.Net website. It barely qualifies as a &#8220;web service&#8221; but by using this with Azure, scaling is incredibly easy. You can build the application to spawn multiple instances at the start, or scale it from Azure. Meaning if this were a true API service, you could monitor your load, and scale it up as needed, very far. If it were on a standard ASP.Net website you&#8217;d have a lot harder time scaling.</p>

<p>And that&#8217;s one of the biggest selling points of Azure in the first place is the easy scaling. We live in a world where your application can become the next big thing overnight, and you need to prepare for it.</p>

<h3>Note</h3>

<p>This is not ready to be a production application. If you&#8217;re serious about building this into a true service, here are some things you should do:</p>

<ul>
<li>Optimize the database calls</li>
<li>sanitize and validate the input (it just takes an open string right now)</li>
<li>better error checking and handling</li>
<li>clean up the JSON output to only include country code and/or name</li>
<li>create a script to interface with it (copy and paste JavaScript is always a good thing)</li>
</ul>


<p>If you do any of these things, fork the repo on <a href="https://github.com/JeremyMorgan/ipcountrycode">GitHub</a> or <a href="https://iplookup.codeplex.com/">CodePlex</a> or contact me and let me know what you&#8217;ve done with it! Enjoy!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top Free Image Optimization Tools]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/free-image-optimization-tools/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T22:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/some-cool-image-optimization-tools</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Making your images load faster is extremely important for page load performance on your site. It makes your pages load faster, which makes for happier visitors, and better search engine performance for your site. Page load time is also a key factor in your bounce rate. Here are some tools I use commonly to reduce image size on my sites.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Mac OSX</h2>

<p>Macs and image editing go hand in hand. A couple of the tools I really like are listed here.</p>

<h3>Shrink O matic</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-2.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>What I like about this software is it&#8217;s very fast and easy to use. You can do things like a straight optimize, rotating and size adjustment. It also supports mass renaming.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> Free. Great tool that works fast and consistently. Simple.</p>

<p><strong>Not so Awesome:</strong> You have to be careful with quality settings, it can get bad very quickly and you may overwrite your originals.</p>

<p><a href="http://shrink-omatic.en.softonic.com/mac">Download Shrink O Matic Here</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>ImageOptim</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-3.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>This one is super easy to use, and great for shaving down size.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> Free, dead simple and really fast. Does what it&#8217;s designed to do.</p>

<p><a href="http://imageoptim.com/">Download ImageOptim Here</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>XNConvert</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-4.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>This is a very powerful program that&#8217;s really good for fine tuning your images. It&#8217;s full of options, everything from changing quality to colors, stripping metadata, adding watermarks and more. Huge feature list to this application and it&#8217;s hard to believe it&#8217;s free.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> It&#8217;s free, and incredibly powerful. More than just image optimization.</p>

<p><strong>Not so Awesome:</strong> Can be a bit overwhelming if you don&#8217;t know what you&#8217;re doing, and there are tons of options that can be confusing. Don&#8217;t let it stop you from using it though.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.xnview.com/en/xnconvert/">Download XNConvert for Mac here</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>iResize</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-5.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>This is a great tool for doing batch operations on images, it&#8217;s extremely powerful and gives you tons of options for converting, resizing and quality adjustments.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome: </strong> Free, and really nice toolset.</p>

<p><strong>Not so Awesome</strong> Interface is a little clunky, and I&#8217;ve never been a fan of separated windows. Still great software though.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.daniele.ch/downloads.php">Download iResize for Mac here</a></p>

<hr />


<h2>Windows Software</h2>

<p>There are still a lot of good options for Windows developers too. Here are a couple great ones:</p>

<h3>RIOT</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-6.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>This is a great tool because it&#8217;s so simple, plus you can visually see what changes are being made. It&#8217;s really good for finding that perfect balance of quality and file size.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> It&#8217;s just a great free package that&#8217;s simple to use, yet powerful.</p>

<p><a href="http://luci.criosweb.ro/riot/">Download RIOT for Windows</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>PNG Gauntlet</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-7.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>For those times when you simply must use those giant PNGs, this tool is really good for sizing them down. It&#8217;s really easy to use and pretty powerful too.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> Free, easy to use and manages to wrangle giant PNGs down to a reasonable size without losing quality.</p>

<p><a href="http://pnggauntlet.com/">Download PNG Gauntlet for Windows</a></p>

<hr />


<h2>Linux Software</h2>

<h3>The Gimp</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-8.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>This old die hard has been around for years. More of an image editing program, but you can use it to reduce and optimize your file size too, plus it&#8217;s fully scriptable.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> It&#8217;s an extremely powerful program that&#8217;s 100% free and community supported.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gimp.org/downloads/">Download the Gimp for Linux</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>XNConvert (again)</h3>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/image-optimization-9.jpg" title="Image Optimization Software" ></p>

<p>I just thought I&#8217;d give an honorable mention to XNConvert once again. They have a version of the software that runs in OSX, Windows and Linux. And since hardly anyone likes to port stuff to Linux I&#8217;m mentioning it again. The Linux version works just as great, and has just as many features.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> Everything I mentioned before, in a fast Linux client.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.xnview.com/en/xnconvert/">Download XNConvert for Linux</a></p>

<hr />


<h3>Jpegoptim</h3>

<p>(No Screenshot available)</p>

<p>This is an executable you run from the prompt, which you may be comfortable with in Linux anyway. It uses lossless optimization with tons of features. Plus it&#8217;s scriptable in BASH, Python or whatever you choose. Can definitely be used for large projects or automated optimization.</p>

<p><strong>The Awesome:</strong> Lean and mean, and highly customizable and scriptable.</p>

<p><a href="http://freecode.com/projects/jpegoptim">Download Jpegoptim for Linux</a></p>

<hr />


<h2>Online Image Optimizers</h2>

<p>Of course with online optimizers you don&#8217;t need to worry as much about your operating environment. These also work very well, so long as you don&#8217;t have a lot of images to work with and have an internet connection.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://tinypng.org/">Tinypng</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kraken.io/">Kraken.io</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.jpegmini.com/">JPEGmini</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.smushit.com/ysmush.it/">Yahoo! Smush it</a></li>
<li><a href="http://tools.dynamicdrive.com/imageoptimizer/">Dynamic Drive Online Optimizer</a></li>
<li><a href="http://webresizer.com/resizer/">Web Resizer</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Most of these work pretty well, though I&#8217;ve always preferred to run optimization on my desktop when I can.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I hope this has helped you find the optimization tool that will help you get your sites loading faster. All of the tools I have featured are free, which is pretty amazing considering the value they give. Consider donating if you can to help fund these projects.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re developing websites, image optimization is one thing to have in your toolkit to really help the speed and responsiveness of your site. Take the time to optimize properly, it will pay off in the long run.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Linux Mint is Awesome]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/linux-mint-is-awesome/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T22:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/why-linux-mint-is-awesome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Linux Mint is one of the most under-rated Linux distribution out there, yet it really does provide a lot of value, even for seasoned Linux hackers. If you haven&#8217;t tried it out yet, you&#8217;re missing out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What do people say about Linux Mint?</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/linux-mint-og.jpg" title="Linux Mint" >The Linux community doesn&#8217;t talk about Mint too much. What most people say is it&#8217;s bloated, too Windows-like and not very modern.</p>

<p>They also complain about non-free software codecs and GNU stuff. It&#8217;s for &#8220;newbs&#8221;. But what if you don&#8217;t care about any of that?</p>

<h3>Linux for Newbs</h3>

<p>First off, I&#8217;m far from a &#8220;Newb&#8221;. I&#8217;ve been using Linux since 1996 or so, and have put in my years with stuff like Slackware, Gentoo etc. Compiling a kernel, or the whole operating system is nothing for me.</p>

<p>If I&#8217;m setting up a server or working with limited hardware I&#8217;ll gladly do it too. A leaned out Arch or Gentoo install is still my choice in certain cases.</p>

<p>But for a desktop? I&#8217;d rather just install something and start working. I&#8217;ve got an I5 and 16 gigs of RAM, don&#8217;t exactly need to optimize a kernel for performance. So if I&#8217;m going to go with a &#8220;drop in and run&#8221; Linux install, what&#8217;s wrong with that? This is a case where I don&#8217;t want to configure stuff all day, I need to work. Linux Mint Shines in this respect.</p>

<h3>It&#8217;s all about the desktop</h3>

<p>Some say that it&#8217;s too &#8220;Windows Like&#8221; but that&#8217;s one of the things I like about it. It&#8217;s a familiar interface, it works so why toy with it? I can&#8217;t stand the Unity interface of Ubuntu and I can tolerate Gnome 3, but my choice is still something like MATE or Cinnamon. It&#8217;s simple, elegant and works great.</p>

<p>Linux Mint focuses on the desktop experience. Many other distributions have admitted they don&#8217;t care about the Desktop, and Ubuntu is still chasing this &#8220;new hotness&#8221; tablet and phone market. But Linux Mint focuses on guys like me, who still use a desktop for work.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/linux-mint-disk-usage.jpg" title="Linux Mint Disk Usage" ></p>

<h4>Stability and ease of use</h4>

<p>I first investigated and installed Linux Mint for my mom, who is by no means a Linux expert. After using it a while, I just really liked the interface, and pain free setup so I started using it for my own projects. Ever since I have noticed one thing about Linux Mint:</p>

<p>It just works. Stuff actually works.</p>

<p>This has always been a big hindrance for Linux distributions, because people get frustrated when they have to edit text files and restart services, then they ask for help online and are told &#8220;RTFM&#8221;. With Linux Mint that doesn&#8217;t seem to be much of an issue. Here&#8217;s what contributes to that ease of use:</p>

<ul>
<li>Stable foundation</li>
<li>Great Package Managers</li>
<li>Great Software Center</li>
<li>Drivers for lots of varied hardware</li>
</ul>


<p>All this combined in a nice stable package makes for a great distribution. Install, update, grab the software you need and go. You can reliably come back to this machine any time without a problem.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/linux-mint-cpu-usage.jpg" title="Linux Mint CPU Usage" ></p>

<h3>Resource Usage</h3>

<p>Remember, it&#8217;s Linux. You&#8217;ll be using a lot less resources than a Windows install. It&#8217;s great for older machines that would otherwise use XP. But if you&#8217;re running something more new and powerful, it&#8217;s also nice to run really smooth. You can pick out packages and services that will speed it up a bit no matter what. You&#8217;re left with a system that uses your resources as efficiently as possible.</p>

<h3>The Bottom Line</h3>

<p>If you&#8217;re the type of person who really wants to get some work done, whether it&#8217;s writing, programming, whatever you need to check out Linux Mint. It really is like Windows only much better. And if you just need a Linux machine to run some hacks or develop some software in an environment only Linux can provide, it&#8217;s your best bet.</p>

<p>You install it, configure it and get to work. If you want to devote hours tweaking and compiling and things like that there are far better distros. If you&#8217;re building a server this isn&#8217;t the right one for you either. But if you want to put together a simple desktop and get to work, <a href="http://www.linuxmint.com/download.php" target="_blank">Linux Mint</a> is the best choice.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Code Smells]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/common-code-smells/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T19:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/common-code-smells</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may have heard the term &#8220;code smells&#8221; lately, it seems its being talked about frequently again. In this short post I&#8217;ll explain what they are, and a few of them you may run across.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>What is a Code Smell?</h2>

<p>A Code Smell is just a fancy word for an indicator of a bigger problem with your code. It&#8217;s language agnostic because you can have code smells in any application. It&#8217;s just a sign of bad construction that you can spot fairly quickly.</p>

<p>The biggest problem with code smells is not that programmers are ignorant about them, it&#8217;s that they choose to ignore them. They&#8217;ll jump into someone&#8217;s code, or their own code and see the problems and make the application work, with the intention of fixing it later. This rarely happens.</p>

<h3>Checking for code smells</h3>

<p>Generally you find code smells when examining code, or doing refactoring. Small cycle refactoring is something you should be doing quite frequently. Often you can take a small method and make it a little better, build some better tests and make it more solid. Eventually you&#8217;ll get through enough of the application to make it solid, or decide on a full rewrite.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/code-smell-1.jpg" title="&#34;Code Smells&#34;" alt="&#34;Code Smells&#34;">The best ways to find code smells are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Casual code inspection</li>
<li>Refactoring</li>
<li>Heuristics analysis</li>
<li>Tools such as PMD, CheckStyle or ReSharper</li>
</ul>


<h3>Common code smells</h3>

<p>So what can you expect to find that might indicate a bigger problem? The list is very long and depends on how deep you choose to inspect your software. But here are some very common ones:</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Repetition</strong> - Easily one of the most common ones. Do you have sections of code repeated all over the place? This is a sure sign of amateur work, and deserves a deeper look.</p>

<p>When refactoring repeated code, you have to effectively search for all instances of that code to get the results you want. While abstracting it into a method is a good fix, it doesn&#8217;t mean you&#8217;re in the clear.</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Needless Complexity</strong> - This is somewhat subjective but most of the time you know it when you see it. Its more complex than it needs to be to solve a given problem and is difficult to comprehend. Needless complexity stems from only a few things:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>A beginning programmer who is making copy and pasted code work to solve a solution.</p></li>
<li><p>A show off who enjoys creating complex solutions to simple problems in order to appear smarter.</p></li>
<li><p>A programmer seeking job security - if they are the only ones who understand it, you can&#8217;t get rid of them (or so they think).</p></li>
<li><p>A programmer who has inherited some nasty code and was forced to build in place. (Arguably the worst case scenario).</p></li>
</ul>


<br />


<p><strong>Rigidity</strong> - While usually considered a good thing, the wrong kind of rigidity can turn your software into a house of cards. When you have methods with too many dependencies that are strictly enforced by breakage, you have a system that can&#8217;t be touched or modified. Two solutions to this are loose coupling and high cohesion.</p>

<p>Make the methods as independent as they can be, yet closely tied to the objects that objects that use them. Break up your objects if they get too big, or have too many dependencies on other unrelated objects.</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Configuration scattered within the code</strong> - This is a basic design flaw that is shown frequently in the wild. The most common one is keeping the database credentials in a database class. This can be a disaster when it gets out of control.</p>

<p>Keep all configurable data (anything anyone can change) at a very high level in a centralized location. This is one of the reasons you see huge config.php or similar files. By having them all in one place you make changes simple and easy. By scattering your data through multiple files and locations you end up creating more time (and technical debt) for the next programmer.</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Immobile code</strong> - Everyone has seen this one. Classes or methods that are marked &#8220;don&#8217;t touch&#8221; are bad and a sign of a much larger problem. If you have something that cannot be modified without taking down the whole system, you&#8217;ve found your weakest link. Fix it immediately.</p>

<p>These are just a few of the basic code smells you&#8217;ll see. There are far more out there but these are pretty high level and common.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/code-smell-2.jpg" title="&#34;Code Smells&#34;" alt="&#34;Code Smells&#34;"></p>

<h3>Where do code smells come from?</h3>

<p>As I stated earlier, it&#8217;s not always programmer ignorance that causes code smells. It usually comes from a rushed design and a disregard for technical debt. They&#8217;re created by a programmer who knows better but wants to just &#8220;get the job done&#8221;. This is a false approach for many reasons.</p>

<p>Technical debt is simply the term for the amount of future work you create when you try to save time up front. You have two choices:</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Do it the right way</strong> - Use best practices and develop a design that is the best of your ability and something you know can scale and grow appropriately. This is your boss&#8217; least favorite method because it takes longer.</p>

<br />


<p><strong>Do it the fast way</strong> - Ignore crucial design decisions that will take too much time to implement. Create a &#8220;hacked together&#8221; design that you keep as clean as you can, but you know it&#8217;s not right. You convince yourself you can always come back later and fix it. This is your boss&#8217; favorite way because it takes much less time.</p>

<p>The problem with the second approach is very simple:</p>

<blockquote><p>The time you save up front making a bad design will come back to haunt you exponentially during maintenance.</p></blockquote>

<p>No matter how good you are or how much you think you can break this rule, it will always prove itself true. You need to educate your boss on the studies done on this, because he/she will not be very happy when maintenance takes considerably more time for &#8220;simple fixes&#8221;.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I hope I&#8217;ve outlined what code smells are and some of the common ones you&#8217;ll see. The message I really want to get across here is do it right the first time. If you don&#8217;t know how to do it right, stop &#8220;winging it&#8221; and start learning more about software design.</p>

<p>Software development is heavily dependent on time. Given enough time developers can make solid gold perfect software, but by the time it&#8217;s finished it&#8217;s no longer needed or the company is questioning where all their money is going to. It&#8217;s a constant battle.</p>

<p>Take a little more time up front to save loads of time in the future, and you&#8217;ll see many of these code smells start to go away.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-30T19:28:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/how-to-install-wireless-network-card-on-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I&#8217;m going to show you how to install a wireless networking card on your Raspberry Pi. I&#8217;m using the ultra cheap Ralink wireless card, but the instructions are similar for any Wireless Device.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Update Your System</h3>

<p>For this tutorial I&#8217;m using Raspian. This is a great beginner OS for the Pi and quite easy to use.</p>

<p>You&#8217;ll want to make sure you&#8217;re at least wired in so you can do an update:</p>

<pre>
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get upgrade
sudo apt-get autoremove
</pre>


<h3>Get Started</h3>

<p>We&#8217;re going to do this from SSH, though it&#8217;s easier to do from the desktop. But you got a Raspberry Pi to learn didn&#8217;t you? Many people use their pi strictly over SSH and don&#8217;t run a desktop at all. I have decided to include those kinds of instructions rather than do it the graphical way.</p>

<h4>1. Plug in your USB device and find it</h4>

<p>Once plugged in, again we&#8217;ll look at our USB devices:</p>

<pre>
lsusb
</pre>


<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-07.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>It looks like in my case it&#8217;s installed, so now we&#8217;ll make a copy of the WPA supplicant file:</p>

<pre>
sudo cp /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf.bak
</pre>


<p>Now open up the file:</p>

<pre>
sudo nano /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf
</pre>


<p>And add the following:</p>

<pre>
network={
    ssid="[YOUR NETWORK SSID]"
    psk="[YOUR NETWORK PASSWORD]"
}
</pre>


<p>It should look like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-06.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>Now, save the file. CTRL + X - Save &#8220;Y&#8221;</p>

<h4>Start up Your Adapter</h4>

<p>Now we need to stop the wlan service:</p>

<pre>
sudo wpa_action wlan0 stop
</pre>


<p>Then bring it back up:</p>

<pre>
sudo ifup wlan0
</pre>


<h4>Test Connectivity</h4>

<pre>
sudo wpa_cli status
</pre>


<p>You should see something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-05.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>If not, double check your network SSID and Password, that&#8217;s the most common problem. You may have a card that isn&#8217;t supported by the Raspberry Pi, if not get a new one! They&#8217;re super cheap and well worth it.</p>

<h3>(Optional) - If You End up Needing a Driver</h3>

<p>Sometimes there are issues that prevent you from loading the drivers for your card. Much of the firmware comes with raspian, but if not you&#8217;ll have to find the drivers for it. You&#8217;ll need a Windows machine to get the drivers you&#8217;ll need (at least for Ralink).</p>

<p>Insert the device and run the driver disk provided. Then after successfully installing it, open up your control panel, and select the properties of the device:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-04.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>Click on &#8220;driver details&#8221;</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-08.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>This will show you the location of the driver files to copy off the machine, you can put them on a USB stick and put them on your Pi from there.</p>

<h4>Get The Drivers off the USB Stick The Hard Way</h4>

<p>I put the driver files on a USB stick. Getting them from the desktop is really easy, but what if you only have SSH access? Don&#8217;t fret. With Raspian it should automount just fine, you only need to find it.</p>

<p>Run the following command to list your USB devices:</p>

<pre>
lsusb
</pre>


<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-03.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>Now, you want to see all the disks that are attached to your system:</p>

<pre>
sudo fdisk -l
</pre>


<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-02.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>As you can see in my case, my USB stick is mounted at /dev/sda1 so the device is connected to my pi. But where is it?</p>

<pre>
mount
</pre>


<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-03.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>There it is! Under /media/MYLINUXLIVE but that probably won&#8217;t be your folder, it will show the drive label you gave it when you formatted it. (I happen to use and love the LinuxLive program whenever I can).</p>

<p>Now I can just look for the drivers on the disk and copy them to a folder in my home directory:</p>

<pre>
cd ~
mkdir usbdriver
cp -r /media/MYLINUXLIVE/driver/* usbdriver/
</pre>


<p>Now the files are copied, safely unmount the drive:</p>

<pre>
sudo udisks --unmount /dev/sda1
sudo udisks --detach /dev/sda
</pre>


<p>Now you&#8217;ll have the drivers you need, but keep in mind the device may not be supported at all.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I hope this has helped to show you how to install a wireless USB card on the Raspberry Pi. Raspian has a lot of firmware already built in and a lot of USB Wifi adapters are supported right out of the box. Wpa_supplicant makes things really easy. I decided to show how to do it from the prompt for those who want to learn more about the prompt, or install from SSH.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi-how-to-wireless-usb-01.jpg" title="How to Install A Wireless USB Network Card on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>The Raspberry Pi is all about learning so I encourage you to experiment with this stuff as much as possible. The worst that will happen is you&#8217;ll need to reinstall the OS. Remember, you&#8217;re learning Linux at the same time which opens a lot of doors for your projects. Enjoy!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like my Rasbperry Pi Tutorials? </h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff with the Raspberry Pi. If you want to get notified every time I post a new article <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/JeremyMorganRaspberryPi"><strong>subscribe to my Raspberry Pi feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=883810"><strong>Sign up for the Raspberry Pi Newsletter</strong></a> spam free!  
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cheap, Fast or Good. Pick any Two]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/software-craftsmanship/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-25T19:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/software-craftsmanship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This old saying in Programming holds true, and I&#8217;m still amazed at the amount of folks out there who still don&#8217;t get it. The matrix is quite simple yet so many folks want it all. Programmers want to build beautiful awesome software built at their own pace, and get lots of money for it. Managers want beautiful awesome software immediately at the lowest price possible. I think there is a way both parties can be satisfied.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Constructing Software is Craftsmanship</h3>

<p>The biggest mistake managers often make is thinking that all software is created equal, it&#8217;s a commodity and [ set task ] should be completed in [ set time ]. This is a common yet expensive mistake. Software building is craftsmanship just like building a house, furniture or many other products out there. By drawing this parallel you can better understand how to get what you want.</p>

<p>Let&#8217;s think about furniture for a minute. What&#8217;s the difference between a handcrafted Italian Leather sofa and an Ikea piece together couch? Thousands of dollars for one thing, but why? Because of the process it takes to make it.</p>

<h4>Italian Leather Sofa</h4>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-fast-good-pick-two-03.jpg" title="Cheap Fast Good" alt="image" /></p>

<p>The Italian Leather Sofa is assembled by hand out of the finest materials. The wood frame is made of high quality wood that is expensive and lasts a long time. It&#8217;s cut with detail and precision, and carefully assembled so it will not come apart easily. Then each piece of leather is cut and inspected, sewn together and put over the most comfortable springs and stuffing that they can find. It is put under a microscope to ensure its comfortable, looks good and can last 100 years or more.</p>

<h4>Ikea Self Assembled Sofa</h4>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-fast-good-pick-two-02.jpg" title="Cheap Fast Good" alt="image" /></p>

<p>The Ikea model is much different. There are machines that mass produce the sections of cheap, readily available wood. If it isn&#8217;t broken and completely decayed it passes. They are slapped together and cheap readily available stuffing, the cloth is stapled over and it flies out the door. They don&#8217;t even assemble it for, but that&#8217;s your job.</p>

<h4>Two very different models</h4>

<p>You have two very different products made in entirely different ways. One sofa is made from the finest materials by skilled craftsmen (or women) and the other is made of commodity items and people pushing buttons on machines. So which one is better?</p>

<p>The answer is neither one. The sofa that&#8217;s better is the one that is better for your particular application and ability to afford it. If you don&#8217;t have $10,000 for a sofa you can at least plant your butt in something that won&#8217;t break the bank. Or maybe you don&#8217;t care enough about sofas to spend that kind of money. Maybe sofas aren&#8217;t really that important to you and you&#8217;d rather spend it on a boat, or you have kids!</p>

<p>Those who have the means and desire for a certain level of quality will purchase the handcrafted sofa and gladly fork over $10,000 for it. They&#8217;ll wait for it to be delivered and pay the premium rather than expecting to take it home for $200 bucks in 15 minutes. Why isn&#8217;t software treated the same way?</p>

<h3>How to Build Your Sofa</h3>

<p>If you&#8217;re in charge of a software project, you have to ask yourself some pretty simple questions, and they&#8217;re the same questions you&#8217;d ask when purchasing a sofa.</p>

<ul>
<li>How much can I afford? (Talent and Tools)</li>
<li>How much time do I have to do it?</li>
<li>How important is each feature?</li>
<li>Is it worth the investment?</li>
<li>Is &#8220;good enough&#8221; a better choice than &#8220;the best&#8221;?</li>
</ul>


<p>With software you have a lot more options and things to think about but the idea is very similar.</p>

<h4>Things that are hard to control</h4>

<ul>
<li>How many developers you have</li>
<li>The quality of those developers</li>
<li>How well they work together</li>
<li>The amount of time your bosses give you</li>
<li>The amount of other projects on the table</li>
<li>The resources you&#8217;ll need (hardware, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>These are difficult to control in most companies. Unless you have the luxury of a giant budget, tons of high quality programmers and &#8220;whenever&#8221; deadlines, these are challenges you&#8217;ll have to work with. Welcome to the real world.</p>

<h4>Things that are easier to control</h4>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Talent of your developers</strong> - You can work hard to find the right people, push them to keep improving and shed the ones who hold you back. It takes time, but it can be done.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The environment</strong> - You can give the programmers a quiet environment free of distractions and give them the tools they need. By holding these things back you&#8217;re also punishing yourself.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Project Priorities</strong> - By careful prioritization of your needs you can have them focus on the important parts of the project. Giving them 200 small things to do at once will only leave with you with low quality unfinished work.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Time given for testing</strong> - In all the places I&#8217;ve worked I have found the managers that give ample time for testing rarely get embarrassed by shipping a product full of bugs that will embarrass them. Sell your boss on the importance of this.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Keep them focused</strong> - I don&#8217;t mean blocking Reddit (though that may help) but keep them focused on a small set of tasks. If programmers have more than 3 concurrent projects going their productivity drops off exponentially. Narrow their work down to a few important things and follow them to they are done.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>You need to focus on the things that are easy to control and make an effort to work on it.</p>

<h4>Focus is the key</h4>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-fast-good-pick-two-04.jpg" title="Cheap Fast Good" ></p>

<p>I consider this step the most important part of the things a manager can control. Focus is more important than the talent of the programmers in my opinion. You can take the best programmers in the world and overload them with one-offs and get junk.</p>

<p>You don&#8217;t see doctors performing heart surgery while talking to another patient about tonsillitis while answering the phone at the front desk. Focus is important. Overloading a developer isn&#8217;t &#8220;pushing them to their peak&#8221; it&#8217;s shooting yourself in the foot.</p>

<h4>The formula for your sofa</h4>

<ul>
<li>Determine what resources you have.</li>
<li>Nail down the specifications and be realistic.</li>
<li>Decide what&#8217;s the most important.</li>
<li>Be realistic about the quality. The difference between good enough and fine art is vast and expensive.</li>
<li>Divide the tasks so the important things are finished first.</li>
<li>Make a solid plan. Plan for the inevitable roadblocks.</li>
<li>Set expectations and hold each person to them.</li>
<li>Give them everything you can to help them complete it.</li>
<li>Show your bosses some awesome stuff.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>Instead of relying on wishful thinking, a proper analysis of what you have  and what you can do will go a long way. You don&#8217;t have to be in the software industry for long before you&#8217;ll see a team of a few people who crank out awesome software way ahead of a big group of programmers that are mismanaged.</p>

<p>Just use common sense and determine where you should put your focus. If you want it fast and cheap, you&#8217;ll have to expect low quality and maybe that&#8217;s ok. If you want fine art, get ready to spend some money and wait a few months. The best place to be is somewhere in the middle.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re building a small widget to show the local weather on your website fast and cheap is fine. If you&#8217;re building a shopping cart and sales portal with customer data you may want to give it some more time and let the programmers build it right. It&#8217;s worth it when it works.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi Cover Photos]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-cover-photos/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-30T00:01:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-profile-images</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I took a picture of my Pi circuitboard for some cover photos, and decided to give them out for others to use. Feel free to download and use these, they are free of branding or watermarking and public domain for personal or commercial uses. Keep checking back as I will likely add more.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Remember to click on the image or link to open the image, not the low quality ones on this page!</p>

<br />


<br />


<br />


<h3>Google+ Profile Cover Photo</h3>

<p>Here is a cover photo for <a href="https://plus.google.com/+JeremyMorgan">Google Plus</a>. It is 2120px x 1192px.</p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-google-plus.jpg" target="_blank"><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-google-plus-small.jpg" title="Raspberry Pi Google+ Cover Photo" ></a></p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-google-plus.jpg">Click here to get it</a></p>

<p><a href="https://plus.google.com/+JeremyMorgan/posts">Connect with me on Google+</a></p>

<br />


<br />


<br />


<h3>Facebook Profile Cover Photo</h3>

<p>Here is a cover photo for <a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeremycmorgan" target="_blank">Facebook</a>. It is 851px x 315px.</p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-facebook-cover.jpg" target="_blank"><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-facebook-cover-small.jpg" title="Raspberry Pi Facebook Cover Photo" ></a></p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-facebook-cover.jpg">Click here to get it</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/jeremycmorgan">Connect with me on Facebook</a></p>

<br />


<br />


<br />


<h3>Twitter Profile Cover Photo</h3>

<p>Here is a cover photo for <a href="https://twitter.com/JeremyCMorgan">Twitter</a>. It is 520px x 260px.</p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-twitter-cover.jpg" target="_blank"><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-twitter-cover-small.jpg" title="Raspberry Pi Twitter Cover Photo" ></a></p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-twitter-cover.jpg">Click here to get it</a></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/JeremyCMorgan" target="_blank">Connect with me on Twitter</a></p>

<br />


<br />


<br />


<h3>App.Net Profile Cover Photo</h3>

<p>Here is a cover photo for <a href="https://alpha.app.net/jeremymorgan" target="_blank">App.net</a>. It is 976px x 234px.</p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-appnet-cover.jpg" target="_blank"><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-appnet-cover-small.jpg" title="Raspberry Pi Facebook Cover Photo" ></a></p>

<p><a href="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/raspberry-pi/raspberry-pi-appnet-cover.jpg">Click here to get it</a></p>

<p><a href="https://alpha.app.net/jeremymorgan" target="_blank">Connect with me on App.Net</a></p>

<br />


<br />


<br />


<h3>Keep checking back here!</h3>

<p>I will likely develop more of these in the coming months, so keep this page bookmarked and share this page! If you do something cool with this contact me and show me! Keep on hacking!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like my Rasbperry Pi Tutorials? </h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff with the Raspberry Pi. If you want to get notified every time I post a new article <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/JeremyMorganRaspberryPi"><strong>subscribe to my Raspberry Pi feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=883810"><strong>Sign up for the Raspberry Pi Newsletter</strong></a> spam free!  
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Setup a LEMP Server in Gentoo]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/linux/how-to-setup-lemp-server-gentoo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T17:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/linux/lemp-server-gentoo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>


<p>You reach a certain point as a developer when a plain old web hosting account just isn&#8217;t enough. Whether you build a project that gets wildly popular or you just start finding custom stuff to do eventually want to run your own Web Server. Today I&#8217;m going to show you how to set up a screaming fast LEMP server you can use to host your projects or websites.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To start this tutorial, I started with a fresh install of Gentoo Linux. You can get one too for about <a href="http://www.linode.com/?r=4ce22489efcec5edefb7af7e815c55675b59120c">$20 USD a month here</a>. I have nothing but praise for this company as they provide fast Virtual servers for a very reasonable price. Check em out!</p>

<h3>The Gameplan</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/gentoo-lemp-server-og.jpg" title="&#34;How to set up a LEMP server in Gentoo&#34;" alt="&#34;How to set up a LEMP server in Gentoo&#34;">
We&#8217;re going to be setting up a nice fast web server. It&#8217;s going to use:</p>

<ul>
<li>NginX</li>
<li>Google PageSpeed Module</li>
<li>SPDY</li>
<li>PHP 5.4</li>
<li>MariaDb</li>
</ul>


<p>This combination will make for a smoking fast server, but it isn&#8217;t easy. We&#8217;ll be compiling Nginx by hand as well to include everything. Don&#8217;t worry it&#8217;s not as bad as it sounds.</p>

<h2>1. Update Gentoo</h2>

<p>Whether you&#8217;re starting from scratch or working with an existing server you&#8217;ll want to make sure your sources are all up to date.</p>

<pre>
emerge --sync
emerge portage
etc-update ( I usually choose -3 )
emerge --update --deep --with-bdeps=y world
</pre>


<p>Go get a cold glass of Orange soda, because this will take a while.</p>

<pre>
etc-update (again)
eselect profile set default/linux/amd64/13.0 (* optional - My linode server profile)
</pre>


<p>Once that&#8217;s done you&#8217;re ready to start building.</p>

<h2>2. Get our Software</h2>

<p>We&#8217;re going to be doing some compiling here so we need to get some sources and put it together.</p>

<pre>
cd ~
mkdir build
cd build
</pre>


<h4>Get Nginx</h4>

<pre>
cd ~
wget http://nginx.org/download/nginx-1.5.1.tar.gz
tar -xvzf nginx-1.5.1.tar.gz
</pre>


<p>We are going to build this scratch, but not yet.</p>

<h4>Get the PageSpeed Module</h4>

<pre>
cd ~
wget https://github.com/pagespeed/ngx_pagespeed/archive/release-1.5.27.3-beta.zip
unzip release-1.5.27.3-beta.zip
cd ngx_pagespeed-release-1.5.27.3-beta/
wget https://dl.google.com/dl/page-speed/psol/1.5.27.3.tar.gz
tar -xzvf 1.5.27.3.tar.gz
</pre>


<h4>Install PHP + FPM</h4>

<p>This is the best way to install PHP on your system. We&#8217;re also going to add in GD and MySQLi, as well as the Geo-IP plugin. These are all optional depending on your needs.</p>

<pre>
echo "dev-lang/php ~amd64" >> /etc/package.keywords
echo "dev-lang/php" >> /etc/package.unmask
echo "dev-lang/php fpm" >> /etc/package.use
echo "dev-lang/php gd" >> /etc/package.use
echo "dev-lang/php mysqli" >> /etc/package.useemerge dev-lang/php
emerge Geo-IP
emerge media-libs/gd 
emerge -av php
</pre>


<p>This will give you PHP with the options we&#8217;ll need for our server.</p>

<h3>Configure and Build Nginx</h3>

<p>For the configuration we&#8217;re going to add in the page speed model, as well as SPDY, GeoIP, gzip static and and an image filter module. This will give us a nice set of options for our web server.</p>

<pre>
./configure --with-http_ssl_module --conf-path=/etc/nginx/nginx.conf \
  --error-log-path=/var/log/nginx_error.log \
  --http-log-path=/var/log/nginx_access.log \
  --pid-path=/usr/local/nginx/nginx.pid \
  --add-module=$HOME/build/ngx_pagespeed-release-1.5.27.3-beta \
  --with-http_spdy_module \
  --with-http_geoip_module \
  --with-http_gzip_static_module \
  --with-http_image_filter_module  \
  --user=nobody \
  --group=nobody \
  --prefix=/usr
</pre>


<p>If you don&#8217;t receive any errors, you&#8217;re ready to make:</p>

<pre>
make && make install
</pre>


<p>Now comes the fun stuff!</p>

<h2>3.Configure NginX</h2>

<p>Now we have to configure Nginx by editing the nginx.conf file.</p>

<pre>
sudo nano /etc/nginx/nginx.conf
</pre>


<p>Note that you can create multiple configuration files and load nginx with them, like profiles but that&#8217;s for another time. Just remember it is an option if you want to try different configs. You can load a file per server, or per website.</p>

<p>For now we&#8217;re going to do it globally throughout the server.</p>

<h4>Tip: Download your Nginx conf file</h4>

<p>This is optional, but it makes life easier. Download your nginx.conf on to your desktop so you can edit it in on your desktop. In OSX or Linux/Unix you can simply type the following at a command prompt:</p>

<pre>
scp root@[your domain or ip address]:/etc/nginx/nginx.conf .
</pre>


<p>This will copy it to whatever directory you&#8217;re in, so you can edit it in GEdit or SublimeText or whatever. If you&#8217;re using Windows you can use something like <a href="http://winscp.net/eng/index.php" rel="nofollow">WinSCP</a> to do same thing.</p>

<p>When you&#8217;re ready to send it back:</p>

<pre>
scp nginx.conf root@[your domain or ip address]:/etc/nginx/nginx.conf
</pre>


<p><strong>Note</strong>
It&#8217;s always good to match your processes to the amount of cores/CPUs your server has. A good way to find out is run this command:</p>

<pre>
cat /proc/cpuinfo | grep processor | wc -l
</pre>


<p>Note this as the amount of worker processes you should set in Nginx.</p>

<h4>Start Configuring</h4>

<p>You will want to create a folder /var/ngx_pagespeed_cache and make it writeable by nginx.</p>

<pre>
mkdir /var/ngx_pagespeed_cache
chown -R nobody:nobody /var/ngx_pagespeed_cache
</pre>


<p>You will also want to create your web folder. For me I chose the /var/www convention:</p>

<pre>
mkdir -p /var/www/innovatsiya.com/public_html
chown -R nobody /var/www/innovatsiya.com/
</pre>




<pre>
ulimit -n 200000

# add the following to keep on reboot:
vim /etc/security/limits.conf
*        -              nofile                  200000
</pre>


<p>Add the following to your nginx.conf</p>

<pre>
user  nobody;
</pre>


<p>Change your worker processes to the number you get from the command below. For my linode it is:</p>

<pre>
worker_processes  8;
</pre>


<h3>nginx.conf</h3>

<p>For my NginX config, I decided to borrow the <a href="http://www.6tech.org/2013/02/nginx-tuning-with-php-fpm-and-memcached/">optimized nginx.conf</a> found on 6tech and do some modifications. Here is what mine looks like:</p>

<pre>
#----------------------------------------------------------------------
# Main Module - directives that cover basic functionality
#
#   http://wiki.nginx.org/NginxHttpMainModule
#
#----------------------------------------------------------------------
 
user nobody;
worker_processes  8;
worker_rlimit_nofile 200000;
 
error_log  /var/log/nginx_error.log;
#error_log  /var/log/nginx/error.log  notice;
#error_log  /var/log/nginx/error.log  info;
 
pid        /var/run/nginx.pid;
 
#----------------------------------------------------------------------
# Events Module
#
#   http://wiki.nginx.org/NginxHttpEventsModule
#
#----------------------------------------------------------------------
 
events {
        worker_connections  4000;
        use epoll;
        multi_accept on;
}

#----------------------------------------------------------------------
# HTTP Core Module
#
#   http://wiki.nginx.org/NginxHttpCoreModule
#
#----------------------------------------------------------------------
 
http {

#----------------------------------------------------------------------
# Google PageSpeed Module
#
#   https://github.com/pagespeed/ngx_pagespeed
#
#----------------------------------------------------------------------

    pagespeed on;
    pagespeed FileCachePath /var/ngx_pagespeed_cache;

    include         /etc/nginx/mime.types;
    include         /etc/nginx/sites-enabled/*;
    default_type  application/octet-stream;
 
    log_format  main  '$remote_addr - $remote_user [$time_local] "$request" '
                      '$status $body_bytes_sent "$http_referer" '
                      '"$http_user_agent" "$http_x_forwarded_for"';
 
    access_log  off;
 
    sendfile    on;
    open_file_cache max=200000 inactive=20s;
    open_file_cache_valid 30s;
    open_file_cache_min_uses 2;
    open_file_cache_errors on;
    tcp_nopush on;
    tcp_nodelay on;
    keepalive_timeout 30;
    keepalive_requests 100000;
    reset_timedout_connection on;
    client_body_timeout 10;
    send_timeout 2;
 
    # Load config files from the /etc/nginx/conf.d directory
    # The default server is in conf.d/default.conf
    include /etc/nginx/conf.d/*.conf;
 
    gzip on;
    gzip_min_length 10240;
    gzip_proxied expired no-cache no-store private auth;
    gzip_types text/plain text/css text/xml text/javascript application/x-javascript application/xml;
    gzip_disable "MSIE [1-6]\.";
 
}

</pre>


<p>Notice we&#8217;ve added in some gzip stuff, set some file cache options and added in google PageSpeed.</p>

<h4>Your Site Config</h4>

<p>Create a folder in your /etc/nginx folder:</p>

<pre>
mkdir /etc/nginx/sites-enabled
</pre>


<p>and create a file in there for your server. I named mine innovatsiya.com but obviously you&#8217;ll need to replace it with your own domain.</p>

<p>Here is what mine looks like:</p>

<pre>
server {

    listen *:80;
    server_name *.innovatsiya.com innovatsiya.com;

    #pagespeed stuff
    location ~ "\.pagespeed\.([a-z]\.)?[a-z]{2}\.[^.]{10}\.[^.]+" { add_header "" ""; }
    location ~ "^/ngx_pagespeed_static/" { }
    location ~ "^/ngx_pagespeed_beacon$" { }
    location /ngx_pagespeed_statistics { allow 127.0.0.1; deny all; }
    location /ngx_pagespeed_message { allow 127.0.0.1; deny all; }

    #root files
    $location / {
            autoindex  on;
            root   /var/www/innovatsiya.com/public_html/;
            index index.html index.php index.htm;
    }

    #PHP files
    location ~ \.php$ {
        include /etc/nginx/fastcgi_params;
        fastcgi_pass 127.0.0.1:9000;
        fastcgi_index index.php;
        fastcgi_param SCRIPT_FILENAME /var/www/innovatsiya.com/public_html$fastcgi_script_name;
    }
}
</pre>


<p>You&#8217;ll notice how I set up a listener, and added in the proper PageSpeed directives, and set up the fastCGI for PHP Scripts.</p>

<p>You may also note that I do not have SPDY configured here. I was having some issues getting proper output, so I have saved that for another time.</p>

<h2>4. Set up MariaDb</h2>

<p>Now we&#8217;re going to set up our database. You might be asking &#8220;Hey, isn&#8217;t the M in LEMP supposed to be for MySQL?&#8221; and the answer is yes and no.</p>

<p>MariaDB has been a better drop in replacement for MySQL for quite a while now. The reasons are outside the scope of this article. If you really want it you can install MySQL, but I wouldn&#8217;t recommend it.</p>

<pre>
echo "dev-db/mariadb" >> /etc/portage/package.keywords
emerge -va dev-db/mariadb
dispatch-conf
./usr/share/mysql/scripts/mysql_install_db --basedir=/usr
/etc/init.d/mysql start
</pre>


<p>You will need to set a password for the root user:</p>

<pre>
/usr/bin/mysql_secure_installation
</pre>


<p>Follow the prompts, and enter your root password. Remove the test and anonymous access stuff for security.</p>

<p>Now type in:</p>

<pre>
mysql -u root -p
</pre>


<p>You should see a screen that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/gentoo-lemp-server-2.jpg" title="&#34;Lemp server in Gentoo&#34;" alt="&#34;Lemp server in Gentoo&#34;"></p>

<p>If so, you&#8217;re ready to go!</p>

<h2>5. Startup the Server</h2>

<p>Check your config file to make sure there aren&#8217;t any errors:</p>

<pre>
nginx -t
</pre>


<p>If there aren&#8217;t any, start it up:</p>

<pre>
nginx
/etc/init.d/php-fpm start
</pre>


<p>To test your server and make sure it&#8217;s output is what you expect, run</p>

<pre>
curl -i http://localhost
</pre>


<p>and you should see something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/gentoo-lemp-server.jpg" title="&#34;Lemp server in Gentoo&#34;" alt="&#34;Lemp server in Gentoo&#34;"></p>

<p>Note the header <strong>X-Page-Speed: 1.5.27.3-3005</strong>. This will show the PageSpeed module installed correctly.</p>

<p>Create some test files in your web root, and after that you should be ready to go!!</p>

<p>You now have a super fast server, dialed in to really handle traffic quickly.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Setting up a server this way is a long, tedious process. But you know you&#8217;re getting the best software compiled exactly how you like it. You can make a lot of changes to this configuration and really nitpick every part till it&#8217;s exactly how you want.</p>

<p>Is it for everyone? Definitely not. You can just as easily build an Ubuntu machine and run a bunch of apt-get commands and get the same thing. The performance difference is pretty negligible. But, that being said if you&#8217;re running a very high traffic site, having a bunch of &#8220;dialed in&#8221; Gentoo linodes will make a difference. The choice is up to you.</p>

<p>This will be an ongoing document, so keep an eye out for changes, and I welcome any feedback you might have in the comments.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dont Build El Caminos]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/dont-build-el-caminos/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T19:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/dont-build-el-caminos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The quickest way to disappoint everyone is by trying to please everyone and software is no different. Sometimes trying to make a &#8220;one size fits all&#8221; solution can get you into trouble.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Remember the El Camino?</h3>

<p>Back in the late 60s GM made the El Camino, which was part car and part truck. While they were wildly popular with some, the fact is it wasn&#8217;t a car or a truck and didn&#8217;t do either very well.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/el-camino-1.jpg" title="El Camino" ></p>

<p>This isn&#8217;t an article to rag on the El Camino but instead talk about quality of &#8220;all in one&#8221; products, especially when it comes to software. One of the biggest problems a programmer creates for themselves is the one size fits all solution.</p>

<blockquote><p>The more features you add to a product the lower quality each feature has to be to meet your deadline.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Where the El Camino Disappoints</h3>

<p>Ok, so you have an idea for this vehicle, and it&#8217;s part car and part truck. The idea is simple, it drives like a car, is low comfortable and you can put a couple dirt bikes in the back of it. Everyone should be happy in reality it&#8217;s quite different.</p>

<p>Those who want it as a car find:</p>

<ul>
<li>It&#8217;s only a two seater.</li>
<li>It doesn&#8217;t have much room.</li>
<li>The bed makes road noise like a pickup</li>
<li>The fuel economy is close to a pickup</li>
<li>The rear of the vehicle is too light for ice and snow</li>
</ul>


<p>Those who want it as a pickup find:</p>

<ul>
<li>You can&#8217;t haul as much weight as a pickup</li>
<li>You can&#8217;t use campers (very popular in the 60s and 70s)</li>
<li>You can&#8217;t tow very much.</li>
<li>It rides low to the ground so it&#8217;s not as safe as a pickup.</li>
</ul>


<p>So as you see, nobody&#8217;s truly happy here. It&#8217;s no big surprise that cars and trucks were still outselling the El Camino. People want something that&#8217;s built for the job.</p>

<h3>How Can This Apply to Software?</h3>

<p>There are a few areas this can apply to software. First is interfaces and features. I&#8217;m no UI expert but I do know that cluttered interfaces are a big mistake. If you&#8217;re selling commercial software it will impact sales, and if you&#8217;re developing internally it will slow down your coworkers. I&#8217;ll give an example.</p>

<h4>Commercial Software</h4>

<p>You&#8217;re building a product that is an HTML editor for building web pages. You have a nice little WYSIWYG interface, file handling and version control. It also has an FTP client interface. These features please the web developers who purchase your software.</p>

<p>But your software is also an optimizing suite that compacts your registry and cleans out old files from your hard drive. It also has a TCP/IP optimizer to speed up your internet, and an image optimizer to make your images smaller and load faster on the web.</p>

<h5>Your software features:</h5>

<ul>
<li>HTML Editor</li>
<li>Registry Cleaner / Compactor</li>
<li>TCP/IP Optimizer</li>
<li>FTP Client</li>
<li>Version Control</li>
<li>Image Optimizer</li>
</ul>


<p>Fancy stuff, right? The software is great for people who want to build websites, and great for people who want a faster computer. Wherever these two intersect you&#8217;ve got some happy customers. But what if they don&#8217;t overlap?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/el-camino-2.jpg" title="El Camino" ></p>

<h5>Problem 1:</h5>

<ul>
<li><p>You&#8217;ll have users who only want to edit websites, not tinker with their computer.</p></li>
<li><p>You&#8217;ll have users who want to optimize their computer, not build websites.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>What happens is you have a bunch of features getting in the way for these two groups. Someone optimizing their computer couldn&#8217;t care less about all this web development stuff and won&#8217;t want to stumble through it to get to their registry cleaner. The opposite is true for the web developer.</p>

<h5>Problem 2:</h5>

<p>Because you tried to cram so many features into this one product you&#8217;re faced with a longer development cycle, or reduced quality. This is especially true if you&#8217;re one person. You have to make a choice to either spend 2 years developing a package with everything, or cut some corners.</p>

<p>This has existed in traditional manufacturing for ages. There&#8217;s a reason handcrafted furniture is more expensive than Ikea.</p>

<h5>Problem 3:</h5>

<p>Your focus has to be divided, not only in development but maintenance and updates as well. You&#8217;re either going to have to focus on the web developers or the system optimizers because they&#8217;re both going to want more features for their tasks.</p>

<h5>Problem 4:</h5>

<p>Your competition will likely focus on one group or the other to &#8220;out feature&#8221; your product as quick as they can. They&#8217;ll develop a web editor with a better WYSIWYG, macros and automatic file versioning and uploading. When a web developer does a direct comparison you&#8217;ll lose out.</p>

<p>Your best bet here is to narrow your focus. Photoshop has been around since 1990 and it&#8217;s the industry standard for a reason. You can&#8217;t compact your registry with it but when working with images there&#8217;s no close competitor. This is because they put all their eggs in one basket and focus on the basket.</p>

<h4>Internal Software</h4>

<p>If you write software for internal use at a company it&#8217;s no different. The purchasing agent is likely going to have needs and features that are far different from a sales rep or the CEO. So why should they all be using one interface?</p>

<p>The problem with building a one size fits all for a company is the fact that your company is full of people who aren&#8217;t very computer literate. It&#8217;s not that they&#8217;re stupid, they likely know their field far better than you do. Your job is to make their job easier. Your tool may make perfect sense to you, especially since you built it but it may be a huge cluttered mess for the person using it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/el-camino-3.jpg" title="El Camino" ></p>

<p>It&#8217;s always best to have your software run from a common database, and even a common core behind the scenes. But the best thing you can do is extract &#8220;views&#8221; for each person to use. While the CEO and Purchasing agent are using the same database or even the same data, their presentation is much different and tailored to their job.</p>

<ul>
<li>internalsite.com/purchasing</li>
<li>internalsite.com/inventory</li>
<li>internalsite.com/shipping</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&#8217;re really good you can have a core that manages everything, but each person only sees and deals with the features they use for their job.</p>

<h3>Behind the Scenes</h3>

<p>When you&#8217;re writing code behind the application the same rules apply. You should always be using the <a href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/single-responsibility-principle/">Single Responsibility Principle</a> wherever it best applies. Instead of making huge objects that try to do everything break down your tasks as much as possible. Bytes are cheap, and since this post has gone on long enough I&#8217;ll cover that in more detail later.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>Focus is everything. There&#8217;s a reason marketing and software development are always so intertwined. Most of the basic rules of marketing apply to software just as well and focus matters. When you take one problem and solve it in the most elegant way possible and put time into it you have happy users.</p>

<p>When you try to solve too many problems with small effort you end up with an El Camino. Always create the right tool for the job and organize your efforts. Your boss or customers will thank you for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sneak Peek at Android Studio]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/android-studio-sneak-peek/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T19:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/sneak-peek-of-android-studio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today at the Google I/O conference they announced a bunch of new things, but one that caught my eye was Android Studio, a new development tool for Android Devices. I decided I had to download it and check it out.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>First Impressions</h3>

<p>I&#8217;ll start off by saying I&#8217;m not really an Android developer. I&#8217;ve toyed around with it, and built one app a couple years ago that&#8217;s basically a web wrapper. But after looking through this program I&#8217;m becoming inspired to pick it up again. Google is clearly trying to pay attention to the developers, who are the lifeblood of the Android platform.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-01.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>One thing I noticed right away is this is clearly based off Eclipse, as many IDE&#8217;s are these days. That&#8217;s not really a bad thing, as Eclipse works really well in many ways and there isn&#8217;t any reason to reinvent the wheel. But if you don&#8217;t like Eclipse, you may not like Android Studio.</p>

<p>Here are some cool options right from the start:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-02.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>This is the kind of stuff you&#8217;d expect for starting a project. There are some options here which version to compile with, and themes available. You also have your basic settings, minimum API, etc. Stuff that helps you so you don&#8217;t get in trouble later down the line. Here you have to make your choice whether to support more features, or be compatible with older devices.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-03.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>Here we have some options, that I don&#8217;t really understand, other than it appears you can have a foreground image and adjust your padding. Probably something to play with later.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-04.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>Here we have a set of templates, which is pretty awesome. Some of the more common ones you might run into are built for you. The options are</p>

<p><strong>Blank Activity</strong> - Creates a new blank activity, with an action bar and optional navigational elements such as tabs and vertical swipes.</p>

<p><strong>Fullscreen Activity</strong> - Creates a new activity that toggles the visibility of the system UI (status and navigation bars) and action bar upon user interaction</p>

<p><strong>Login Activity</strong> - Creates a new login activity, allowing users to enter an email address and password to log in to or register with your application</p>

<p><strong>Master / Detail Flow</strong> - Creates a new master/detail flow, allowing users to view a collection of objects as well as details for each object. This flow is presented using two columns on tablet-size screens and one column on handsets and smaller screens. This template creates two activities, a master fragment, and a detail fragment.</p>

<p><strong>Settings Activity</strong> - Creates a new application settings activity that presents alternative layouts on handset and tablet-sized screens.</p>

<p>These give you a nice set of options to start. The most intriguing to me is the Master / Detail flow, which I definitely want to learn more about.</p>

<h3>Note about Performance</h3>

<p>I noticed it&#8217;s a little sluggish loading and building, but I did run this on an older Centrino machine with 4 gigs of RAM. Keep in mind this is an early release, and it&#8217;s an old machine. When actually coding in the IDE it seems to run really well, and I haven&#8217;t had too many quirks.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-05.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>I can&#8217;t say I&#8217;m thrilled with that memory usage though.</p>

<h3>Inside the IDE</h3>

<p>The IDE looks a bit familiar if you&#8217;ve ever used Eclipse, but it&#8217;s got a lot of nice features, and is clearly tailored for Android development.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-06.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>It has everything where you&#8217;d expect it to be, and the syntax highlighting is pretty nice. Code collapsing and most of the features you&#8217;d expect are here.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-07.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>One thing I noted that&#8217;s pretty awesome is the Version Control integration.</p>

<p>There are a lot of awesome tools in this IDE, too many to describe in one article, but the code analysis ones really stand out:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-08.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>I ran some tests on my basic project and found a lot of things worth looking at:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-09.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>Lots of refactoring options. This kind of stuff saves you a lot of time and can even help improve your coding.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-10.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>Overall I think hardcore Android developers are really going to like what&#8217;s included here.</p>

<h3>A few issues</h3>

<p>I mentioned it&#8217;s a little sluggish, but that&#8217;s to be expected with bleeding edge software on old hardware. It&#8217;s only a little slower than Eclipse runs on this machine. But I noticed that I couldn&#8217;t get it to find my phone or my Kindle Fire when I tried:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-11.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>And it wouldn&#8217;t let me run anything in the AVD:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/android-studio-download-12.jpg" title="Android Studio" ></p>

<p>Though this could be a configuration error. I couldn&#8217;t find where to change it and gave up, but I&#8217;ll come back to it soon.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>I&#8217;m sure in the coming days you&#8217;ll hear some complaints and talk of it just being a &#8220;reskinned Eclipse&#8221; but I think Google is going in the right direction with this. There are tons of features I haven&#8217;t even dug into yet, and many I don&#8217;t know as I&#8217;m not really an Android developer at this time. But I did use the ADT environment for Eclipse and I do see some obvious improvments.</p>

<p>Google is showing that the see the value in their developers and are giving them some pretty awesome tools to succeed. There were also some great gaming APIs released today and what we&#8217;re seeing is Google preparing developers to take their popular platform to the next level. It&#8217;s an exciting time to be a programmer indeed.</p>

<p>Download it and try it out!</p>

<p><a href="http://developer.android.com/sdk/installing/studio.html" target="_new"><h3>Download Android Studio Here</h3></a></p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intro to ASP.NET MVC 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/c-sharp/how-to-asp-mvc/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T19:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/c-sharp/intro-to-asp-dot-net-mvc-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>


<p>The ASP.Net MVC 4 framework was introduced in August of last year and it boasts tons of improvements over MVC 3. If you&#8217;re considering building a large application in .Net, you should consider MVC 4 for your project. Today we&#8217;re going to take a look at it and build a quick website in MVC 4.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What you&#8217;ll need</h3>

<p>In order to complete this tutorial you will need Visual Studio. I have decided to use Visual Studio Express 2012 for Web to do this tutorial. I made this choice because it&#8217;s a free download and not everyone can afford the professional version of Visual Studio, but if you&#8217;re using Visual Studio 2010 or 2012 you can still go along as well.</p>

<h4>Software needed:</h4>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/visualstudio/eng/downloads#d-2012-express" title="Microsoft Visual Studio Express for Web">Microsoft Visual Studio Express 2012 for Web</a></strong> (or a licensed version of Visual Studio 2010/2012)</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.microsoft.com/web/webmatrix/" title="Microsoft Web Matrix 2">Microsoft Web Matrix 2</a></strong> - This is a handy little stack to help organize your server and projects for development</p>

<p><a href="http://www.asp.net/mvc/mvc4" title="Microsoft MVC download"><strong>Microsoft ASP.Net MVC 4</strong></a> - The package you&#8217;ll need to install to deploy this on your website.</p>

<p>Keep in mind all of this is free! The MVC package is also Open Source. It&#8217;s nice to see Microsoft come around with stuff like this.</p>

<h3>Let&#8217;s get set up</h3>

<p>One of the things every Visual Studio has been raving about lately is the NuGet package manager, for good reason. It makes setting things up super easy. We want to make sure we have it installed for our project.</p>

<p>Go to <strong><em>Tools -> Extensions and Updates</em></strong></p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>And make sure the <strong>NuGet Package Manager</strong> is installed:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-2.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>This will enable you to install stuff into your website easily. They have a lot of great plugins and templates available.</p>

<h3>Create the Project</h3>

<p>Go to the start section and click &#8220;New Project&#8221; or select it from the File menu. You want make sure to select an ASP.NET MVC 4 Web Application.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-3.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>On the next screen, select &#8220;Internet Application&#8221;. As you can see there are various options here, feel free to play around with them and see what you come up with.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-4.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>Now you&#8217;ve created your new MVC application. Let&#8217;s take a look at it. If you press F5 you&#8217;ll see it&#8217;s already assembled into a site. But that doesn&#8217;t do much yet.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-5.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<h3>The parts of your MVC application.</h3>

<p>You&#8217;ll notice the controller is opened automatically. Let&#8217;s take a look at it and see what it does:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>public class HomeController : Controller
</span><span class='line'>    {
</span><span class='line'>        public ActionResult Index()
</span><span class='line'>        {
</span><span class='line'>            ViewBag.Message = "Modify this template to jump-start your ASP.NET MVC application.";
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>            return View();
</span><span class='line'>        }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>        public ActionResult About()
</span><span class='line'>        {
</span><span class='line'>            ViewBag.Message = "Your app description page.";
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>            return View();
</span><span class='line'>        }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>        public ActionResult Contact()
</span><span class='line'>        {
</span><span class='line'>            ViewBag.Message = "Your contact page.";
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>            return View();
</span><span class='line'>        }
</span><span class='line'>    }</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>As you can see this is the &#8220;Home&#8221; controller that extends the controller class. Since Home is your default route it will control what&#8217;s seen on your site root.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>public ActionResult Index()
</span><span class='line'>    {
</span><span class='line'>        ViewBag.Message = "Modify this template to jump-start your ASP.NET MVC application.";
</span><span class='line'>        return View();
</span><span class='line'>    }</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This is the &#8220;Index&#8221; method, and it&#8217;s not too tough to guess it&#8217;s place. This is what shows up when you hit a root directory. Whatever you put in here gets shown on the page. But let&#8217;s look a little closer inside the method.</p>

<pre>
ViewBag.Message = "Modify this template to jump-start your ASP.NET MVC application.";
</pre>


<p>The ViewBag is a wrapper object used to store dynamic data for the ViewData dictionary object. There are some arguments circulating about which one to use, but since Visual Studio stuffs this in, we&#8217;ll use it. Let&#8217;s change it to something else:</p>

<pre>
ViewBag.Message = "This is my first MVC Project!";
</pre>


<p>Where does this data go? If you open up /Views/Home/Index.cshtml you&#8217;ll see where this object is used.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-6.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>First, at the top you&#8217;ll see where the ViewBag.Title property is assigned a value:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>@{
</span><span class='line'>    ViewBag.Title = "Home Page";
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This is a part of the Razor engine and it&#8217;s how you change the title of the page when it loads. You can also change it later. Then further down the page you&#8217;ll see:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>&lt;h1>@ViewBag.Title.&lt;/h1>
</span><span class='line'> &lt;h2>@ViewBag.Message&lt;/h2></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>As you can see, this is where the ViewBag.Message you changed earlier will go.</p>

<p>One advantage of this is you can make the text displayed dynamic, pulled from a database, object or other data source without touching the design. You can also use this for localization if needed. The Razor engine is pretty sweet, this is just scratching the surface of it.</p>

<h3>Creating a New Page</h3>

<p>By now you&#8217;ve probably figured out that the methods in the controller correlate with pages: Index(), About(), and Contact(). So let&#8217;s look at creating a new page. We will be creating a page located at &#8220;http://(your site url)/Home/Newpage&#8221;.</p>

<p><strong>1. Create a new ActionResult Method</strong></p>

<p>Inside your HomeController, create a new method:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>public ActionResult Newpage()
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>  ViewBag.Message = "This is a new page! ";
</span><span class='line'>  return View();
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The home controller is found in /Controllers/HomeController.cs</p>

<p>What is this? The HomeController is the controller for your home directory and each ActionResult is a function of that controller or page. In our case the url would be</p>

<p>Http://www.yoursite.com/home/newpage</p>

<p>Each action must have a view, which we&#8217;ll create next.</p>

<p><strong>2. Create a view page</strong></p>

<p>A view is simply an HTML page that displays data and interacts with the controller. You create views for pages or parts of pages, such as menus.</p>

<p>In the /Views/Home/ folder, create a new view by right-clicking on the /Views/Home folder and selecting &#8220;New View&#8221;:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-7.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>You&#8217;ll see a dialog box that looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-8.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>As you can see, this dialog box has a few options. For the view engine, you can choose Razor or ASPX(C#). Choose Razor for this, and leave the rest of the options open. You can create a strongly typed view that&#8217;s based of an object, but we&#8217;ll leave that for another tutorial. Hit add.</p>

<p>You&#8217;ll see the page now in your views folder.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-9.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>Open up that page, and you&#8217;ll see the following code:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>@{
</span><span class='line'>    ViewBag.Title = "Newpage";
</span><span class='line'>}
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>&lt;h2>Newpage&lt;/h2></span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Add some html for fun in there. Also, add the following line:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Hi! Today is @DateTime.Now.DayOfWeek</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Save the file, and press F5 to run.</p>

<h3>Your new MVC Page</h3>

<p>To load the page you just created, type in</p>

<p>/home/newpage</p>

<p>after the URL. For instance my local URL is http://localhost:59312/home/newpage but yours may vary. You should see something like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-mvc-asp-4-10.jpg" alt="How to Program ASP.Net MVC 4" /></p>

<p>This is your newly created view! Feel free to experiment with the views and the Razor view engine. The best way to learn is to break it!</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>In this tutorial we built a very basic MVC 4 page in ASP.Net. I hope it gets you excited enough to start really experimenting. The MVC package really does a lot of the work for you, you can actually create whole websites without a lot of code at all. But I do hope you will dig into the code, and get rid of some that atrocious HTML that&#8217;s generated and fiddle around.</p>

<p>In a future tutorial I&#8217;ll cover the Entity Framework and show you how easy it is to add data to your MVC Pages. Sign up for my newsletter and you&#8217;ll know right when it&#8217;s posted!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where to Find a Cheap Computer in Oregon]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/portland/cheap-computers-oregon/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-21T14:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/portland/where-to-find-a-cheap-computer-in-oregon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post isn&#8217;t going to be much use for the majority of my audience, but I am creating this post because I am often referring people to these places, and wanted to create a nice page to send them to.</p>

<p>This is a small list of computer recyclers in my area that I&#8217;ll be updating and spreading around. I&#8217;m a huge fan of computer recycling and low cost computing, if you&#8217;re curious you should look around in your area for some similar non profit recyclers!</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Can I use a recycled computer?</h3>

<p>The answer to this isn&#8217;t always yes. If you&#8217;re looking for the latest and greatest, or you play games (real games not Facebook games) you won&#8217;t be able to find what you need here. But mostly what I get asked about is: &#8220;I need a computer for school but don&#8217;t want to pay a lot&#8221; and that&#8217;s one area where recycled computers shine. Here&#8217;s what you can use recycled computers for:</p>

<p><strong>Schoolwork</strong> - High School, college etc. Creating documents and reports, etc. A cheap computer running <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice</a> will work just fine.</p>

<p><strong>Programming</strong> - A high end machine is nice for programming but not really necessary. You can do web development on just about anything for instance. I do most of the work for this website on a 2004 Powerbook, because it&#8217;s basic text editing. My Windows stuff is done on a 2007 Toshiba Laptop.</p>

<p><strong>Office Management</strong> - Again using a cheap older computer with <a href="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice</a> and you can do pretty much anything a high dollar new machine will do, only a bit slower. But if you&#8217;re saving $1000 it might be worth the price.</p>

<p><strong>Kid Computers</strong> - If you want a computer for your kids to browse the internet and play learning games an old computer works great. If you&#8217;re ready for the challenge, you can install Linux on it where most versions have TONS of educational software for free. Take <a href="http://www.edubuntu.org/">Edubuntu</a> for a spin and check out all the awesome stuff they have.</p>

<p>This list could be a lot longer but it&#8217;s not the purpose of the article. Basically if you aren&#8217;t playing online games, ripping videos or something of that sort you might notice that a new computer isn&#8217;t a whole lot better than an older one.</p>

<h3>Cheap Computer Recyclers in Oregon</h3>

<p>Here is a list of people I&#8217;ve dealt with personally and really like. You can walk in with a couple hundred bucks and come out with a decent desktop or laptop that works great. They test their equipment, set it up and don&#8217;t try to upsell your or rip you off.</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>Computer Drive Connection - Cornelius Oregon</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://computerdriveconnection.com/">Their Website</a></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-computer-oregon.jpg" title="Where to find a cheap computer in Oregon" ></p>

<p>Since this one is closest to my hometown I&#8217;ve been sending a lot of people here. The guy running it is great, he&#8217;s very knowledgeable and honest. Just tell him what you need to use a computer for and he&#8217;ll steer you right. Great prices as well.</p>

<p>For instance, I picked up a 20&#8221; LCD flatpanel monitor there recently for $100. Worked great, no scratches or dead pixels. It&#8217;s the 3rd or 4th monitor I&#8217;ve picked up there that works great.</p>

<p><a href="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=909+N.+Freemont+Lane+%C2%A0%C2%A0%C2%A0Cornelius,+Oregon+97113&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;ll=45.524397,-123.060812&amp;spn=0.002161,0.004823&amp;hnear=909+N+Fremont+Ln,+Cornelius,+Oregon+97113&amp;gl=us&amp;t=h&amp;z=18">Map to their location</a></p>

<p><strong>Phone:</strong> (503) 992-0180</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>Eco Binary - Beaverton Oregon</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ecobinary.com/">Their Website</a></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-computer-oregon-1.jpg" title="Where to find a cheap computer in Oregon" ></p>

<p>I just recently discovered this place, and they treated me really well. I picked up a laptop for $100 (the Core2 Toshiba) and an old G4 machine for a server. The dusty old G4 had been sitting a while but he said &#8220;yes, it works if not bring it back&#8221;. Great policy, but the machine did work exactly as advertised.</p>

<p>Again it&#8217;s a good place with knowledgeable people and no sales pressure. It&#8217;s family run and they do a great service for the community and their customers.</p>

<p><a href="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=8240+SW+Nimbus+Ave.+Beaverton,+OR+97008&amp;hnear=8240+SW+Nimbus+Ave,+Beaverton,+Oregon+97008&amp;gl=us&amp;t=h&amp;z=16">Map to their location</a></p>

<p><strong>Phone:</strong> (503) 352-4991</p>

<hr>


<p><strong>Free Geek</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://www.freegeek.org/">Their Website</a></p>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/cheap-computer-oregon-2.jpg" title="Where to find a cheap computer in Oregon" ></p>

<p>For those in the Portland Metro area this is another great service you gotta check out. They are a non profit that offers free computers (if you qualify) and free computer classes as well. But if you don&#8217;t qualify for a free one or you feel like supporting them you can visit their <a href="http://www.freegeek.org/thrift-store/">thrift store</a> and purchase items at a great price. All purchases support their mission.</p>

<p><a href="https://maps.google.com/maps?q=1731+SE+10th+Avenue,+Portland,+OR&amp;hnear=1731+SE+10th+Ave,+Portland,+Multnomah,+Oregon+97214&amp;gl=us&amp;t=h&amp;z=16">Map to their location</a></p>

<p><strong>Phone:</strong> (503) 232-9350</p>

<hr>


<h3>Recycled computers are awesome!</h3>

<p>I will be researching more of these types of companies locally and adding to this list. There&#8217;s many reasons getting a recycled computer makes sense, you save money and help keep this stuff from hitting landfills. You support families and volunteers rather than giant corporations.</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re not from the Northwest Oregon area, search for some recyclers in your area! Even if you already have your dream machine it may be worth getting a machine to tinker with for projects, media servers etc. Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is MVC?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/what-is-mvc/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-10T18:04:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/what-is-mvc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The MVC or Model View Controller architecture is a software pattern that&#8217;s become very popular over the last few years. With this article we&#8217;ll take a look at MVC, how it works and how it&#8217;s used.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What is MVC?</h3>

<p>MVC is not really a package or a tangible object but more of an idea or methodology. Microsoft has a software package for ASP.Net called <a href="http://www.asp.net/mvc" title="Microsoft MVC">Microsoft MVC</a> but it&#8217;s not really a product as much as an implementation of the pattern. There are other projects out there similar to this, but you can build a Model, View and Controller in any language.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s simply a way of building software that has many benefits, here&#8217;s a rough idea of how it works:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/what-is-mvc-1.jpg" title="What is MVC?" ></p>

<p>The MVC Model consists of three parts:</p>

<p><strong>Model</strong> - Usually tied to a database or other data source, this section only deals with raw data in the application.</p>

<p><strong>View</strong> - This is the display functionality of the application. Usually a web page or User Interface.</p>

<p><strong>Controller</strong> - This is what ties the other two together. It takes commands from the user, retrieves or updates data in the model and communicates information back through the view.</p>

<p>When these three parts work together you get a separation of concerns in your code. You have a model which only cares about itself, it merely processes requests and manipulates or sends data. The View is concerned only with displaying the data and providing a way for the user to communicate their next move. The controller merely coordinates the two.</p>

<h3>MVC on the Web</h3>

<p>So how is this applied in real life? Here&#8217;s a diagram of a web site using MVC:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/what-is-mvc-2.jpg" title="What is MVC?" ></p>

<p>First the visitor opens a web browser, and a command is sent to the controller to show a web page. The controller then contacts the model, which pulls raw data from the database and passes it back to the controller. The controller then passes it to the view which formats the data and mixes it with html to create a web page you can view.</p>

<h3>Advantages of MVC</h3>

<p>MVC frameworks do not offer any additional performance or features to your application, they exist primarily to help the programmer(s).</p>

<p><strong>Separation of Concerns:</strong> - This is a tenet of good design and encapsulates your functions and creates a defined interface. For example someone working on a model only has to worry about interfacing with a database and getting the right information, but doesn&#8217;t have to worry about browser compatibility at the same time.</p>

<p><strong>Code Reuse:</strong> - Because of the separation of concerns with MVC you can reuse your code easily. If you have a great view object that displays pages well on a phone for example, you can reuse that same code easily as a view in another application.</p>

<p><strong>Decoupling:</strong> - Another tenet of good design, keeping your software decoupled means easier changes down the road. For instance if you&#8217;re changing database servers from one vendor to another do you want to rewrite or modify your model, or the whole piece of software? With a well implemented MVC framework you can do it in a fraction of the time.</p>

<p><strong>Testability</strong> - While having your software decoupled and separated is good for programming, it&#8217;s great for testing. You can take a section of code and easily run various tests on specific parts of the program as you go along and those tests can be very focused. Are you looking for data integrity? Expected display? When functions are clearly grouped testing becomes far simpler and more organized.</p>

<h3>Disadvantages of MVC</h3>

<p>So if MVC is the greatest thing since sliced bread then why isn&#8217;t everyone doing it all the time? It&#8217;s a mistake to think MVC is a magic bullet that will cure all your software problems.</p>

<p><strong>Complexity</strong> - MVC adds a layer of complexity to any project. This is a cost that&#8217;s acceptable with a huge payoff and that usually comes from large projects that would be complex anyway. But a small app or widget is better off without such complexity. Sometimes MVC just adds more work to a task that would otherwise be simple.</p>

<p><strong>Can affect performance</strong> - If you have a simple widget that uses 20 lines of code and a simple task it could very well be slower when done in an MVC environment. Again it comes down to cost vs benefit, and MVC doesn&#8217;t always win.</p>

<p><strong>You may be using non MVC code in your project</strong> - You could be stuck with code that is already built with model and view functionality tightly integrated. Trying to mix and match in an MVC model can cause more problems than it solves.</p>

<p><strong>Additional Resource Usage</strong> - MVC frameworks are avoided in low resource environments such as embedded software and programs designed to run very lean. When you&#8217;re building a web app on a big server the fractional increase in memory usage is well worth the benefits but if you&#8217;re counting bytes or squeezing something onto a chip it&#8217;s best to avoid them.</p>

<h3>Summary</h3>

<p>I hope I&#8217;ve given you a general idea of what MVC is and you may even be considering it for your next project. Generally the following projects are best suited for MVC frameworks or design:</p>

<ul>
<li>Large web applications</li>
<li>Large projects</li>
<li>Projects with multiple programmers</li>
<li>Projects with separate designers and programmers</li>
<li>Anything that may scale larger in the future</li>
<li>Projects that will have an API</li>
</ul>


<p>In future articles I will go over how MVC is changing and being implemented in today&#8217;s application. It&#8217;s been around since the 80s and the classic MVC model is changing and adapting to new trends. I&#8217;ll also do a tutorial showing how to do a basic MVC design with PHP. Till then send me your comments and questions if you have them!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I improved the speed of my mobile app by over 1000%]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/making-firecom-faster/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-03T20:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/making-firecom-faster</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple years ago I wrote an app called &#8220;FireCom&#8221; for the Android phone that&#8217;s basically just a listing of active Fire and EMS calls in Washington County, Oregon. I never expected too many people to use it and gave it away so I didn&#8217;t put a lot of time into it. As it turned out a lot of people started using it, so lately I decided to put a little more effort into it.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What is FireCom?</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-5.jpg" title="FireCom Android App" > I created the application in February 2011, and it spawned from being a volunteer firefighter and looking up calls on our <a href="http://www.wccca.com/PITS/">Joint CAD Incident Tracking System</a> which a listing of calls in our local county plotted out on a Google map.</p>

<p>There is also a <a href="http://www.broadcastify.com/listen/feed/1102/web/?rl=rr">link to audio</a> there as well, and when I was in the Fire Academy I listened a lot to learn everything from radio etiquette to fireground strategy. Turns out there&#8217;s a lot you can learn by listening to this stuff.</p>

<p>But if you tried to look up any of this data on your phone, it was less than great. Sometimes curiosity takes over as well, when you see a speeding ambulance or fire truck you want to know where they are going or what&#8217;s going on.</p>

<p>This is why I created the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.jeremymorgan.wccca&amp;hl=en">FireCom app</a>, I wanted to make something quick and easy someone could bring up on their phone that would show that information. After some research and digging around I found a script written by <a href="http://gary.moonrize.com/">Gary Kee</a> that scraped the calls from an RSS feed to post on Twitter. It was the perfect missing link.</p>

<h3>How the first FireCom worked.</h3>

<p>The first iteration of the FireCom app parsed the XML feed and displayed the results on the screen using Java. I found it to be pretty slow and really unreliable, so it didn&#8217;t last very long. I&#8217;m not an expert Java or Android programmer and didn&#8217;t want to mess with it very much. So instead I decided to stick with what I was good at, and created a PHP page on this site that scraped the data and formatted it into nice little page. Then I created a WebView wrapper that simply brought up the page.</p>

<p>It worked great for a couple years. As I said I didn&#8217;t expect many people to use it and I used it myself for quite a while. But after a while I would started getting emails from people about it, and talking to fellow firefighters who were using it all the time. The two complaints I kept hearing were how slow it was sometimes, and how the map function didn&#8217;t work well. It took a few seconds to load because it was basically set up like this:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-1.jpg" alt="FireCom Android App" /></p>

<p>Basically the WebView loaded up a PHP page on my server. The PHP page pulled the data from the output XML in realtime from the WCCCA server. It parsed it and created some HTML for the page formatted for the phone and did some cleanup of the text and station names. I decided using a WebView would be the best way so I could make updates and changes without making someone download the updates constantly.</p>

<p>The biggest problem was it was accessing this XML file every time someone loaded up the app, and sometimes it was quite slow. It&#8217;s a large XML file that&#8217;s dynamically generated and it puts out a lot of data that had to be parsed, and only a small portion is actually used. There were times when it really took a long time to load, and on a phone that can be even worse. Here was the average load time the night I upgraded the app:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-2.jpg" alt="FireCom Android App" /></p>

<p>As you can see the time isn&#8217;t that great. There are a few reasons, the slow XML process I described, plus the repeat view isn&#8217;t going to be any different. I turned off caching on this script because it&#8217;s live data that shouldn&#8217;t be cached. 4 seconds may not seem like much, but it&#8217;s really pretty sluggish and I think folks using the app just got accustomed to pressing the icon and waiting for the results. Could I fix that? I came up with a new way to solve that very problem.</p>

<h3>The new, improved FireCom</h3>

<p>For the second iteration, I decided to do a few things to speed it up.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Remove excess HTML</strong> - Anything that wasn&#8217;t absolutely required was removed. Should have done this a long time ago.</li>
<li><strong>Compressed HTML</strong> - I removed all returns and whitespace from the file. Just a single line of html was pushed out.</li>
<li><strong>Optimized the WCCCA image</strong> - This is a small thing, but on a mobile connection it can make a difference. I also set caching for this image.</li>
<li><strong>Refactored the application</strong> - This is the process I&#8217;ll detail below.</li>
</ul>


<p>I refactored the application by changing the way I pulled the data. Instead of accessing the XML file every time a user brought up the app, I created a script to pull the data, and generate the feed.php file.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-3.jpg" alt="Firecom Android App" /></p>

<p>The feed.php file is now actually only a single line of HTML. But since there are already about 2000 people pointing to that file, it wouldn&#8217;t be wise to change it. So now I have a feedloader that reads the xml and generates a static PHP file to read, so the load time is considerably faster:</p>

<p><img src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-4.jpg" alt="FireCom Android App" /></p>

<p>Over 10 times faster in fact. The repeat view is a little faster as well due to the image caching. So now the app is way faster, and my job is done right? Not exactly.</p>

<h3>Now we have a new problem</h3>

<p>So if you&#8217;ve looked at the new system you&#8217;ve figured out that the feedloader does the heavy lifting and just generates a static PHP file for the app. This is where the majority of the speed improvements have come from. But this file has to be run pretty frequently, because with the old system feed.php was in realtime, now it is a static file. If I don&#8217;t update it then the users are stuck with old information.</p>

<p>Since I&#8217;m hosted on a Windows server, I can&#8217;t just whip up a quick CRON job for this. I set up Windows Scheduler to run this file every 2 minutes or so. After watching it very closely and doing some testing I found that it is very spotty. Sometimes it will run every two minutes consistently, and sometimes it will run every 5, or even ten minutes. Since I am not the admin of this server there isn&#8217;t much I can do.</p>

<h3>Let&#8217;s crowd source it!</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/firecom-android-app-6.jpg" title="FireCom Android App" >
I was thinking of having it randomly run the feedloader when someone loads the app. Maybe one out of every 100 people visiting would trigger the feedloader and that would refresh the feed.php for everyone. But this seemed like a terrible solution because I&#8217;m picking users at random to have a slow experience. While 99 people get a snappy page, that one person is stuck loading the file for the feed. Not a great solution.</p>

<p>I decided to let the scheduled task continue to run in it&#8217;s spotty fashion, and I put a &#8220;last updated&#8221; timestamp into the page. Then I put a &#8220;refresh data&#8221; button in that runs the feed loader. This also takes 4-5 seconds but at least the user is <em>choosing</em> to take that time in order to see the newest version of the page. I&#8217;m not springing it on people expecting people do it without their permission.</p>

<p>In the future I&#8217;m likely going to migrate this to a Linux server and set up a cron job. I&#8217;ve never really seen those fail, but Windows scheduler is a different story. I may even set up something on my Raspberry Pi to do the job who knows.</p>

<h3>Lessons Learned</h3>

<p>What I learned from this, is the value of making a WebView app when you can. This way you can do all kinds of stuff behind the scenes without bothering the user with updates all the time. Naturally not every app can be made into a WebView but if you can, it&#8217;s worth trying.</p>

<p>I also learned every little bit counts, and while moving feed.php to a static file was the big performance improvement, the little stuff like html compression helps too. When it comes to page speed, every tiny thing counts. When you&#8217;re dealing with mobile devices and varying amounts of bandwidth it does a lot of good to cut down the amount of data you&#8217;re transferring. For some people it&#8217;s even saving them on their bill.</p>

<p>Overall I&#8217;m glad people are using this app, and I hope the faster version works better for them.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you want to be notified every time a new tutorial is posted?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
If you want to see more tutorials like these <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=889026"><strong>subscribe to our spam free newsletter</strong></a> and get them instantly in your inbox or feed reader.
If you want to get all my updates, <a href="http://feedburner.google.com/fb/a/mailverify?uri=jeremymorgan/NJwt&amp;loc=en_US"><strong>subscribe to the main RSS feed</strong></a> here.
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Build C# apps on Your Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/how-to-c-sharp-raspberry-pi/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-28T20:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/tutorials/raspberry-pi/how-to-run-net-on-your-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to run and build .Net applications on your Raspberry Pi? In this article I&#8217;ll show you how. With Mono you can develop and run .Net applications on your Raspberry Pi. I got a few emails about this, so I decided to create a quick tutorial.</p>

<!-- more -->




<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like my Rasbperry Pi Tutorials? </h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff with the Raspberry Pi. If you want to get notified every time I post a new article <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/JeremyMorganRaspberryPi"><strong>subscribe to my Raspberry Pi feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=883810"><strong>Sign up for the Raspberry Pi Newsletter</strong></a> spam free!  
</div>


<h3>What&#8217;s the Purpose here?</h3>

<p>If you&#8217;re thinking of running your favorite Windows .Net applications, or setup a fancy ASP.NET server, you may be disappointed. While Mono does a great job and the Raspberry Pi performs great for what it is, I wouldn&#8217;t say this solution is ready for the big leagues, and definitely not something you want to do in a production or commercial environment.</p>

<p>If you want to tinker around and learn C#, and maybe build a few cool apps this is a great way to do it. The Raspberry Pi is a great tool for learning, and that&#8217;s the purpose of this project.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-raspberry-pi-net-1.jpg" title="How to run .Net on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>There are tons of MONO applications available in Raspbian but we&#8217;re only going to cover some basics.</p>

<h3>Install Mono</h3>

<p>Mono is an awesome project that brings .Net to Linux. It&#8217;s available for the Raspian image, and super easy to set up.</p>

<p>Update your repos:</p>

<pre>sudo apt-get update</pre>


<p>And install the Mono Runtime:</p>

<pre>sudo apt-get install mono-runtime</pre>


<p>This one could take a while. It updated a lot of stuff on my system.</p>

<pre>sudo apt-get install mono-mcs</pre>


<p>Note about MonoDevelop: You can install this on a soft float install of Raspian or Arch but it&#8217;s not the best performing application in these conditions. Mono still has a lot of problems with the Pi that need to be ironed out, and MonoDevelop is a long ways off.</p>

<h3>Build a quick application.</h3>

<p>Load up LeafPad (or whatever your favorite text editor is) and create a file called monotest.cs and save it somewhere where you&#8217;ll find it.</p>

<p>Enter the following code:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>using System;
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>namespace Test
</span><span class='line'>{
</span><span class='line'>    class Program
</span><span class='line'>    {
</span><span class='line'>        public static void Main()
</span><span class='line'>        {
</span><span class='line'>            Console.WriteLine("Hello! This is a Mono app running on {0}", Environment.OSVersion);
</span><span class='line'>        }
</span><span class='line'>    }
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now, open up an LX Terminal and go to where this file is located (I just put it in a folder called monotest as well). Type in the following:</p>

<pre>
mcs monotest.cs
</pre>


<p>This should only take a couple seconds. Then list the files in your directory (using the ls command) you will see a new file:</p>

<pre>
monotest.cs
monotest.exe
</pre>


<p>Now, you can run the monotest.exe by typing in:</p>

<pre>
mono monotest.exe
</pre>


<p>You will see something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://images.jeremymorgan.com/how-to-raspberry-pi-net-3.jpg" title="How to run .Net on Raspberry Pi" ></p>

<p>And you&#8217;re ready to go! If you see this, that means it worked.</p>

<h3>So what can you do now?</h3>

<p>You can write basic C# console applications all day with this setup. You can build neat automation items, and even some GUI stuff if you really want to dig into it. You can write .Net 1.0 - 4.0 applications with varying success. The most valuable thing you do is learn some C# basics and experiment like crazy.</p>

<p>C# is one of my favorite languages, so it&#8217;s awesome to see options for playing with it without being forced to use Windows and Visual Studio, which are great tools but expensive for hobbyists. As I said this is nowhere near something for production use, but excellent for tinkering and learning which is of course what the Raspberry Pi is all about!</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like my Rasbperry Pi Tutorials? </h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff with the Raspberry Pi. If you want to get notified every time I post a new article <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/JeremyMorganRaspberryPi"><strong>subscribe to my Raspberry Pi feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=883810"><strong>Sign up for the Raspberry Pi Newsletter</strong></a> spam free!  
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Single Responsibility Principle]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/single-responsibility-principle/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-20T21:04:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jeremymorgan.com/blog/programming/the-single-responsibility-principle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There&#8217;s a lot of genius in simplicity. This applies to many things in life and definitely in software development. SRP, or Single Responsibility Principle is one of the foundations building better software. It&#8217;s a good way to keep code working as expected, and to avoid painting yourself in a corner.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Do one thing and do it well</h3>

<p>The Single Responsibility Principle guides simplicity, and the rule itself is strikingly simple: There should never be more than one reason for a class to change. This is easier said than done of course, but the idea is if you have more than one reason to change a class, then you should break it into two classes.</p>

<p>This goes for methods as well, as sometimes folks tend to cram a bunch of functions into a method. The problem with that is, when part of that method changes drastically, you may have to modify the signature or output of the method. Overloading can help there, but it&#8217;s still better to separate tasks as much as possible. Creating another class or method doesn&#8217;t cost a thing.</p>

<p>I know OOP design usually dictates getting as much done in an object as you can, but this can lead to growing pains down the road. This is where extending and inheritance can really come in handy.</p>

<h3>A SRP Violation</h3>

<p>Ok one of the biggest violators I have seen is mixing presentation with data. With the MVC movement in full swing you don&#8217;t see as much of it anymore, but it still happens. Take the following class from a blog app:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>class Page {
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public function drawIndex() {
</span><span class='line'>      $this->getArticle($id);
</span><span class='line'>      // some code to output HTML
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>  
</span><span class='line'>  private function getArticle($id){
</span><span class='line'>      // query the database for the latest article
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Why is this bad? It looks pretty simple, and it&#8217;s pretty easy to use. The reason it&#8217;s bad is because it does two separate things, it gets and article from the database, then it outputs html. This is not only a violation of the Single Responsibility Principle but Separation of Concerns as well.</p>

<p>What happens when you change databases? This happens all the time. You have now made drastic changes to the getArticle function, and maybe even the output that comes from the database. This is bad design to have this coupled with your presentation code and even puts it at risk. Plus, let&#8217;s say you want to display the output to JSON as well. Where would that method go? Lumping it all together creates a huge mess later down the road.</p>

<p>Not to mention the fact that your designers and your DBA might both be dipping into the same class&#8230; is that something you really want?</p>

<h3>The Solution</h3>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>class Page {
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public function drawIndex() {
</span><span class='line'>      $data = $model->getArticle($id);
</span><span class='line'>      // functions to output HTML
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>}
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>class Model {
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  public function getArticle($id){
</span><span class='line'>      // query the database for the latest article
</span><span class='line'>      
</span><span class='line'>  return $data;
</span><span class='line'>  }
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once you break it into two classes you create a Separation of Concerns. The Page class generates web pages, and the Model gets data from your database. The page doesn&#8217;t care what the model is doing as long as it takes in data (the article id) and outputs data (the article) as expected. You can change the model to connect to any data source you want, and the Page class doesn&#8217;t care.</p>

<p>And the Page class is now free to output data any way it wants. If you want to create some html, you can create a method to do that, output some JSON, XML whatever, with the same data from the model. By separating them you give yourself a lot more freedom down the road to change and modify.</p>

<blockquote><p>Just remember, if there is more than one reason to change, split it up.</p></blockquote>

<h3>When to implement the Single Responsibility Principle</h3>

<p>In theory you want to do this from the very beginning. As you&#8217;re designing your application you should always keep this in mind. In practice it&#8217;s not always easy and sometimes you just have to get your project finished. This is where refactoring comes in.</p>

<p>You should always go back and refactor your code at some point because business rules change, requirements change and things get added on and subtracted. Good code refactoring can really improve your development process. Remember, you&#8217;re optimizing for humans here, and the easier it is for you or another programmer to make changes the better off you&#8217;ll be down the road.</p>

<p>For more information about the Single Responsibility Principle, check out <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0137208715/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1789&creative=390957&creativeASIN=0137208715&linkCode=as2&tag=webfootcentra-20">Principles of Object Oriented Analysis and Design</a> by James Martin.</p>

<br />


<div class="subscribefooter">
<h4>Do you like articles like this?</h4>
<div class="rssbutton"></div>
I&#8217;m constantly hacking on stuff and writing about happenings in the programmer world. You can <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/jeremymorgan/NJwt"><strong>subscribe to my feed</strong></a> here, or you can <a href="http://www.feedblitz.com/f?sub=339769"><strong>get the programmer newsletter</strong> spam free!</a>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
