<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jeremy Morgan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials: How to work with arrays in PHP</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</guid>
      <description>What is an array? Arrays are common to almost every programming language. An array is simply an ordered map of values, indexed so you can find these values, called elements. These elements can be of multiple datatypes, and can be ordered any way you want.
Array([a] =&amp;gt; 1[b] =&amp;gt; 2[c] =&amp;gt; 3)The Two types of arrays in PHP There are two types of arrays in PHP, associative and enumerative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become a React Developer in a Weekend</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-07-become-a-react-developer-in-a-weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-07-become-a-react-developer-in-a-weekend/</guid>
      <description>If you want to be a React Developer, there&#39;s a lot to learn. You can get started in a weekend. Yes, in a single weekend, you can learn React and start developing some cool applications!
Here&#39;s how I would approach it.
Friday Night Ok, instead of binge-watching some TV show Friday night (no judgment, I&#39;ve been there), you could spend the time learning the basics of React. If you&#39;ve never touched React or done anything with it, The Big Picture is the place to start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can you use FreeBSD for a Developer Machine in 2020?</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-19-freebsd-dev-machine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-19-freebsd-dev-machine/</guid>
      <description>FreeBSD is a solid choice on a server, and it&#39;s ubiquitous in the infrastructure world, but how does it hold up as a desktop machine? As a developer workstation? I found out.
I&#39;ve been considering moving my blog back to a FreeBSD web server. I&#39;d hosted it that way for years and recently switched it to a Linux machine so I could make Octopress work properly. It uses some old, outdated Ruby gems, and it just seemed easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stop Fearing the Whiteboard. Conquer It.</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-22-stop-fearing-the-whiteboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-22-stop-fearing-the-whiteboard/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s time we stopped fearing, complaining, and arguing about whiteboard coding interviews.
With a solid plan, a little skilling up, and some practice, you can master the whiteboard interview. We can argue for days about the validity of this type of interview, but the fact is many organizations require it. So are you going to let this obstacle stop you from getting the job you want? Of course not. Let&#39;s tackle the whiteboard interview, and defeat it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Developer Tool You Can&#39;t Live Without</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-10-nimble-text-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-10-nimble-text-review/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m introducing a text / code generation tool that you will fall in love with. If you&#39;re a developer or someone who works with text or tabulated data you need this tool.
It&#39;s called Nimble Text and it&#39;s awesome. Here&#39;s how the developer of Nimble Text describes it:
 You can be more awesome at your job by keeping this tool always within reach.
NimbleText is a text manipulation and code generation tool available online or as a free download.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>