<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jeremy Morgan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials: How to work with arrays in PHP</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</guid>
      <description>What is an array? Arrays are common to almost every programming language. An array is simply an ordered map of values, indexed so you can find these values, called elements. These elements can be of multiple datatypes, and can be ordered any way you want.
Array([a] =&amp;gt; 1[b] =&amp;gt; 2[c] =&amp;gt; 3)The Two types of arrays in PHP There are two types of arrays in PHP, associative and enumerative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Become a React Developer in a Weekend</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/how-to-learn-react/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/how-to-learn-react/</guid>
      <description>If you want to be a React Developer, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot to learn. You can get started in a weekend. Yes, in a single weekend, you can learn React and start developing some cool applications!
Here&amp;rsquo;s how I would approach it.
Friday Night Ok, instead of binge-watching some TV show Friday night (no judgment, I&amp;rsquo;ve been there), you could spend the time learning the basics of React. If you&amp;rsquo;ve never touched React or done anything with it, The Big Picture is the place to start.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can you use FreeBSD for a Developer Machine in 2020?</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/freebsd/freebsd-developer-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/freebsd/freebsd-developer-2020/</guid>
      <description>FreeBSD is a solid choice on a server, and it&amp;rsquo;s ubiquitous in the infrastructure world, but how does it hold up as a desktop machine? As a developer workstation? I found out.
I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering moving my blog back to a FreeBSD web server. I&amp;rsquo;d hosted it that way for years and recently switched it to a Linux machine so I could make Octopress work properly. It uses some old, outdated Ruby gems, and it just seemed easier.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>