<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jeremy Morgan</copyright>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Attacks on my Server</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-10-analyzing-attacks-on-my-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-10-analyzing-attacks-on-my-server/</guid>
      <description>I was casually doing a security audit on my blog recently and decided to look a little deeper into my security logs. With a bit of Linux command line kung fu, some Golang, and Google sheets, I was able to get a pretty good idea of where the attacks are coming from.
To start, I&#39;m using CentOS to host my site, so I checked out /var/log/secure. This log is where authentication logs are stored on my server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with WSL</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-15-getting-started-with-wsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-15-getting-started-with-wsl/</guid>
      <description>Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL) is awesome.
It gives you the power to use Linux within your Windows system. A Linux shell can be difficult to learn, but the payoffs are incredible. You can become insanely productive with it. I encourage every Windows developer to give this a try.
Early in my development career, I was a Unix/Linux developer, and I loved working with the shell. In 2010 I was thrust into the world of Windows with GUIS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Set Up Hugo on Pop!_OS</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-03-04-hugo-on-popos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-03-04-hugo-on-popos/</guid>
      <description>If you want to generate static websites (like this blog) then Hugo is the package for you. There are several cool things about Hugo, the biggest being performance. It compiles static sites faster than any other static site generator I&#39;ve used.
In the last tutorial, I showed how to set it up and deploy to a small Linux server, and in this article I&#39;ll show you how to set it up for personal development in Pop!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out the Pinebook Pro - a $200 ARM Laptop</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-16-testing-pine64-laptop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-16-testing-pine64-laptop/</guid>
      <description>The Pinebook Pro is a $200 laptop that runs a couple of ARM processors, and it promises a lot. Does it deliver? After what seemed like an eternity waiting, mine arrived and here&#39;s what I think.
I used this thing for a few days casually to get a feel for what it&#39;s like, and this is my first impression.
As a note, you can get a $100 Pinebook here as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using a Raspberry Pi as Your Development Server</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-31-raspberry-pi-dev-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-31-raspberry-pi-dev-server/</guid>
      <description>In this tutorial, I will show you how to set up a Raspberry Pi 4 as a development (or testing) server. You can use this as a place to push your code and test it in a web browser. For the demo, I&#39;ll use a React application, but with a few modifications, you can build just about anything with it.
For this project, I&#39;m using a Canakit Raspberry Pi 4 Complete Kit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s the big deal with Pop!_OS?</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-25-pop-os-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-25-pop-os-review/</guid>
      <description>A new Linux distribution has been popping up in discussion circles everywhere, it&#39;s Pop! OS. What is it and why are people so crazy about it?
I&#39;ll give you my first impressions of Pop!_OS and whether I think you should consider it for your development machine.
Pop! OS Saved Me There I was, giving a presentation for a group of people on Blazor earlier this month. I&#39;d spilled tea on my Windows laptop a couple days prior, so I did the presentation with my MacBook Pro.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>