<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jeremy Morgan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Stop Fearing the Whiteboard. Conquer It.</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/whiteboard-interview-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/whiteboard-interview-tips/</guid>
      <description>It&#39;s time we stopped fearing, complaining, and arguing about whiteboard coding interviews.
With a solid plan, a little skilling up, and some practice, you can master the whiteboard interview. We can argue for days about the validity of this type of interview, but the fact is many organizations require it. So are you going to let this obstacle stop you from getting the job you want? Of course not. Let&#39;s tackle the whiteboard interview, and defeat it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trying out the Pinebook Pro - a $200 ARM Laptop</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/linux/blog/linux/pine64-pro-laptop-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/linux/blog/linux/pine64-pro-laptop-review/</guid>
      <description>The Pinebook Pro is a $200 laptop that runs a couple of ARM processors, and it promises a lot. Does it deliver? After what seemed like an eternity waiting, mine arrived and here&#39;s what I think.
I used this thing for a few days casually to get a feel for what it&#39;s like, and this is my first impression.
As a note, you can get a $100 Pinebook here as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Developer Tool You Can&#39;t Live Without</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/blog/programming/tools-csv-text-nimbletext/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/blog/programming/tools-csv-text-nimbletext/</guid>
      <description>I&#39;m introducing a text / code generation tool that you will fall in love with. If you&#39;re a developer or someone who works with text or tabulated data you need this tool.
It&#39;s called Nimble Text and it&#39;s awesome. Here&#39;s how the developer of Nimble Text describes it:
 You can be more awesome at your job by keeping this tool always within reach.
NimbleText is a text manipulation and code generation tool available online or as a free download.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Blazor is Going To Change Web Development</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/blazor/blog/blazor/what-is-blazor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/blazor/blog/blazor/what-is-blazor/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I wrote an article about building and deploying a Blazor app without touching a Windows machine and realized maybe I should take a step back and explain what Blazor is and why anyone would use it. It&#39;s still fairly new to most in the front end development world, but it&#39;s awesome and you should check it out.
So what is it, exactly? Blazor is a framework from Microsoft that you can use to develop interactive client-side Web UIs with C#.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Learn Computer Programming</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/how-to-start-programming-for-free/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2007 13:29:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/how-to-start-programming-for-free/</guid>
      <description>So you want to be a computer programmer? Want to write software? Here is how you can get started with this awesome hobby / profession right away, for next to nothing. I first wrote this article back in 2008 and a lot has changed since then, so I decided to start it over completely.
Last update in 2016Tips for getting started If I were to narrow down the two things that will ultimately determine your success here it&#39;s this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Huge RPC Ping list</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/my-huge-rpc-ping-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2007 13:29:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/blog/programming/my-huge-rpc-ping-list/</guid>
      <description>I ping a lot of RPC Services when I post. If you dont know what an RPC ping is, read here. This is a good way to let these services know you&#39;ve updated. While it may not be necessary to use all these sites, it doesn&#39;t hurt to have them. Here is a list of 254 services good at the time of this writing.
http://api.my.yahoo.com/RPC2http://api.my.yahoo.com/rss/pinghttp://bblog.com/ping.phphttp://bitacoras.net/ping/http://blog.goo.ne.jp/XMLRPChttp://blogdb.jp/xmlrpchttp://blogmatcher.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>