<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tutorials on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</title>
    <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/tutorials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tutorials on Jeremy Morgan :: Tech Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jeremy Morgan</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jeremymorgan.github.io/categories/tutorials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tutorials: How to work with arrays in PHP</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 17:43:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/tutorials/php-tutorials/how-to-work-with-arrays-in-php/</guid>
      <description>What is an array? Arrays are common to almost every programming language. An array is simply an ordered map of values, indexed so you can find these values, called elements. These elements can be of multiple datatypes, and can be ordered any way you want.
Array([a] =&amp;gt; 1[b] =&amp;gt; 2[c] =&amp;gt; 3)The Two types of arrays in PHP There are two types of arrays in PHP, associative and enumerative.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create Your Own Blog for 5 Dollars a Month</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-29-create-your-own-blog-5-dollars-a-month/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-02-29-create-your-own-blog-5-dollars-a-month/</guid>
      <description>Blogging about tech is fun. Having your own blog allows you to help others, polish your skills, and maybe get you a job.
Blogging on other sites such as Medium, Dev.To, etc can be really fun. I do that all the time. But having your OWN site to manage your content is important as well. This gives you freedom to do things exactly as you want, and you don&#39;t have to worry about losing your content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Set Up Hugo on Pop!_OS</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-03-04-hugo-on-popos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-03-04-hugo-on-popos/</guid>
      <description>If you want to generate static websites (like this blog) then Hugo is the package for you. There are several cool things about Hugo, the biggest being performance. It compiles static sites faster than any other static site generator I&#39;ve used.
In the last tutorial, I showed how to set it up and deploy to a small Linux server, and in this article I&#39;ll show you how to set it up for personal development in Pop!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using a Raspberry Pi as Your Development Server</title>
      <link>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-31-raspberry-pi-dev-server/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeremymorgan.github.io/2020-01-31-raspberry-pi-dev-server/</guid>
      <description>In this tutorial, I will show you how to set up a Raspberry Pi 4 as a development (or testing) server. You can use this as a place to push your code and test it in a web browser. For the demo, I&#39;ll use a React application, but with a few modifications, you can build just about anything with it.
For this project, I&#39;m using a Canakit Raspberry Pi 4 Complete Kit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>